<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Tissue Eng</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Tissue Eng</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TEJ</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptej</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Tissue Engineering</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2041-7314</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26977284</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4765821</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2041731415618342</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2041731415618342</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Review</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Impact of mechanical stretch on the cell behaviors of bone and surrounding tissues</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Hye-Sun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2041731415618342">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2041731415618342">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-2041731415618342">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jung-Ju</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2041731415618342">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-2041731415618342">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Hae-Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2041731415618342">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-2041731415618342">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-2041731415618342">4</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp2-2041731415618342"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lewis</surname>
            <given-names>Mark P</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-2041731415618342">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wall</surname>
            <given-names>Ivan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2041731415618342">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2041731415618342">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1-2041731415618342"><label>1</label>Department of Biochemical Engineering, University College London, London, UK</aff>
      <aff id="aff2-2041731415618342"><label>2</label>Department of Nanobiomedical Science and BK21 Plus NBM Global Research Center for Regenerative Medicine, Dankook University Graduate School, Cheonan, South Korea</aff>
      <aff id="aff3-2041731415618342"><label>3</label>Institute of Tissue Regeneration Engineering (ITREN), Dankook University, Cheonan, South Korea</aff>
      <aff id="aff4-2041731415618342"><label>4</label>Department of Biomaterials Science, School of Dentistry, Dankook University, Cheonan, South Korea</aff>
      <aff id="aff5-2041731415618342"><label>5</label>Musculo-Skeletal Biology Research Group, School of Sport, Exercise and Health Sciences, Loughborough University, Loughborough, UK</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="corresp1-2041731415618342">Ivan Wall, Department of Biochemical Engineering, University College London, Torrington Place, London WC1E 7JE, UK. Email: <email>i.wall@ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp>
        <corresp id="corresp2-2041731415618342">Hae-Won Kim, Institute of Tissue Regeneration Engineering (ITREN), Dankook University, Cheonan 330-714, South Korea. Email: <email>kimhw@dku.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <season>Jan-Dec</season>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <elocation-id>2041731415618342</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2016</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mechanical loading is recognized to play an important role in regulating the behaviors of cells in bone and surrounding tissues in vivo. Many in vitro studies have been conducted to determine the effects of mechanical loading on individual cell types of the tissues. In this review, we focus specifically on the use of the Flexercell system as a tool for studying cellular responses to mechanical stretch. We assess the literature describing the impact of mechanical stretch on different cell types from bone, muscle, tendon, ligament, and cartilage, describing individual cell phenotype responses. In addition, we review evidence regarding the mechanotransduction pathways that are activated to potentiate these phenotype responses in different cell populations.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Flexercell</kwd>
        <kwd>mechanical strain</kwd>
        <kwd>bone</kwd>
        <kwd>cartilage</kwd>
        <kwd>muscle</kwd>
        <kwd>tendon</kwd>
        <kwd>ligament</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
          <meta-value>January-December 2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-2041731415618342">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The bone and surrounding tissues experience many different types of mechanical loading. For example, compressive forces are experienced and tolerated well by articular cartilage. Shear stress resulting from interstitial fluid flow is tolerated in bone tissue and in tendons and ligaments, tensile stretch is tolerated in order to maintain skeletal anatomy. The effect of different forms of mechanical loading of cells has been extensively studied in vitro and in animal models and human subjects, where it is commonly reported to have stimulatory effects on those cells. In fact, fluid flow&#x2013;induced shear stress actively enhances cellular events that potentiate bone formation and remodeling,<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> and compressive loading of articular chondrocytes stimulates their proliferation capacity. In this review, we will focus specifically on the impact of mechanical stretch on bone and surrounding cell responses and in particular, the use of the Flexercell system as a means of applying that stretch.</p>
      <p>In 1985, the first reported use of flexible-bottomed plates for studying the effect of mechanical stimulation on cell cultures was made.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> The plates used a computer-controlled vacuum device to apply negative pressure to the underside of the membrane. When the vacuum was applied, the membrane on which firmly adhered cells were attached was stretched downward and consequently, a strain was imparted on the cells adhered to that membrane. A number of parameters under the control of the operator included the magnitude of pressure, waveform, frequency, duration, and incorporation of rest period over the time course of the experiment. As the system is easy to set up and these various parameters are easy to control, the Flexercell system has been a very good platform with which to study the effect of mechanostimulation in many different contexts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2041731415618342">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="fig1-2041731415618342" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Experimental setup of the Flexercell system for applying strain to cell populations. (a) Schematic representation of the computer-controlled Flexercell system that applies strain to cell monolayers in custom-made six-well plates. (b) Cross-sectional diagram of one well of a six-well Flexercell plate at rest (top) and upon application of the vacuum (bottom). (c) Strain can be applied in a variety of ways including uniaxial and equiaxial.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2041731415618342-fig1"/>
      </fig>
      <p>One huge benefit of the widespread use of this system is that even though the many studies of bone and surrounding cell responses use different strain regimes (magnitude, frequency, duration, etc.), the fact that the base technology applies strain using a common method of application means that some comparability between different studies can be made. Strain is applied either uniaxially or biaxially, generally in two-dimensional (2D) culture (although there are some exceptions to this, where a three-dimensional (3D) culture module is used to characterize compressive force) on silicone membranes coated with type I collagen. Dishes can also be coated with other extracellular matrix (ECM) molecules too making it possible to characterize the effect of mechanical stretch on cells anchored to different ECM components, providing a 2D model of in vivo mechanical stimulation of tissues.</p>
      <p>In the bone and surrounding tissues, mechanical signals are continually generated and experienced by the numerous cell types that make up the component tissues. Understanding the role of mechanotransduction and its effects at the cellular level can greatly enhance our understanding of the role of mechanical signals in maintaining normal healthy musculoskeletal physiology and also provide some insight to mechanisms of pathogenesis, for instance, during chronic overuse injury. In the following sections, we review the ever-growing body of the literature that describes bone and surrounding cell responses to mechanical strain applied using the Flexercell system.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section2-2041731415618342">
      <title>Effect of mechanical strain on bone cell phenotypes</title>
      <p>During bone loading in vivo, macroscale forces are transmitted to osteocytes through the canalicular network in the form of microscale shear stresses caused by rapid displacement of interstitial fluid. Prolonged cyclic loading of bone leads to increased mineralized tissue density and bone mass. It was hypothesized some time ago that mechanical force was a positive regulator of bone formation creating a shift in bone homeostasis toward the anabolic state, characterized by enhanced bone-forming activity by osteoblasts and a reduction in bone resorption by osteoclasts.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> In addition to shear stress caused by fluid flow (see above; reviewed by Brindley et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> and Yeatts and Fisher<sup><xref rid="bibr2-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>), tensile stretch applied to cells via physical deformation of culture surfaces<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="bibr6-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x2013;<xref rid="bibr7-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> can enhance key cellular and molecular events that lead to bone formation. A summary of notable studies is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-2041731415618342">Table 1</xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="table1-2041731415618342" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summary of Flexercell studies and key findings using osteoblastic cells.</p>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2041731415618342-table1"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell type</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage of differentiation</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch device and regime</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key findings</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine osteocytic (MLO-Y<sub>4</sub>)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 5% elongation, 10&#x2009;min, 0.05&#x2013;1&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrogen receptor involved in strain-mediated pro-survival signaling via ERK</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aguirre et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">24-h culture in differentiation medium (early differentiation)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 3%&#x2013;9% strain, 8&#x2009;h, 1&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High strain increased proliferation, migration, VEGF and bFGF production</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhatt et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low strain increased OCN and OPN</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat osteoblast (ROS 17/2.8) and mouse osteoblast (MC3T3-E1)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 1% elongation, 10&#x2009;min, 0.25&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain-induced rapid phosphorylation of ERK2 and FAK and activation of Ras/Raf/MEK pathway</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boutahar et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr10-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human osteosarcoma (TE-85)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteosarcoma</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> intermittent strain of 3 cycles/min consisting of 10&#x2009;s strain, 10&#x2009;s rest, 15&#x2013;60&#x2009;min or 1&#x2013;3&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain-induced reorganizated distribution of integrins and increased &#x3B2;1 but not &#x3B1;&#x3BD; mRNA levels</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carvalho et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human osteosarcoma (SaOS-2)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteosarcoma</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 5%&#x2013;12% elongation, 8&#x2013;24&#x2009;h, 0.05&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased expression of TGF&#x3B2;1, IGF1, bFGF, IL6, but no change in IL1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cillo et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse osteoblast (CIMC-4)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-osteoblast</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> biaxial strain at 0.5%&#x2013;2%, 24&#x2009;h, 0.16&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain caused a reduction in RANKL, but upregulated OSX and RUNX2 via ERK1/2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fan et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Rat osteoblast (ROS17/2.8) and human osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cells; 24-h post-plating</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 1% elongation, 1.5&#x2013;150&#x2009;min, 0.05&#x2013;5&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expression of soluble VEGF isoforms (121, 165) under low frequency</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faure et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expression of matrix-bound VEGF isoforms (206, 189, 165, 145) under high frequency</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat osteoblast (ROS17/2.8)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mature osteoblasts (3&#x2009;weeks in differentiation medium)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 1% elongation, 10&#x2009;min, 0.05&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch-induced activation of Egr-1 and nuclear translocation of NF-&#x3BA;B</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Granet et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat osteoblast (ROS 17/2.8) and mouse osteoblast (MC3T3-E1)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early osteoblast</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 1% elongation, 15 cycles/min (2-s deformation period followed by a 2-s neutral position)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Induced phosphorylation of FAK, PYK2, paxillin and HIC5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guignandon et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine calvarial osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early osteoblast (7&#x2013;10&#x2009;days post-plating)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 2.5%&#x2013;3% elongation, 3&#x2013;24&#x2009;h, 0.3&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch resulted in the activation of canonical Wnt signaling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hens et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human fetal osteoblast (SV-HFO)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation medium</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bioflex loading stations, 0.4%, 5&#x2013;60&#x2009;min or 7&#x2013;21&#x2009;days, 0.05&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch-induced phosphorylation of ERK1/2 pathways dependent on differentiation stage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jansen et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr18-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse osteoblast (MC3T3-E1)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#x2009;h in differentiation medium</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 0.25%&#x2013;2.5%, 1&#x2009;Hz, 15&#x2009;min/day for 7&#x2009;days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall increased RANKL due to increased membrane-bound RANKL but decreased soluble RANKL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Rat osteoblast and mouse osteoblast (MC3T3-E1)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 10%&#x2013;12%, 0.1&#x2009;Hz either one single maximal strain load every 6&#x2009;h or continuous strain for 24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch increased DNA synthesis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knoll et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALP decreased in response to strain and combined strain/TGF&#x3B2; treatment</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human osteoblast (HOB)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 2.5% elongation, 0.1&#x2009;Hz, intermittent strain 1&#x2009;h, strain 3&#x2009;h, and rest for 48&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased DNA synthesis and IL6 production</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liegibel et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No effect on ALP, COL I or OPG production</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Human osteosarcoma (SaOS-2)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x2009;days post-plating</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 5%&#x2013;12.5% strain, 24&#x2009;h, 0.5&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low strain led to increased COL I and COL III expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liu et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High strain led to decreased COL III expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse osteoblast (MC3T3-E1)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 7%&#x2013;24% elongation, 3 cycles/min, 1&#x2013;24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased expression of VEGF and M-CSF</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Motokawa et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr22-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse osteoblast (MC3T3-E1)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 0%&#x2013;9% elongation, 3&#x2013;24&#x2009;h, 0.3&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch promoted COX2 but not COX1 expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Narutomi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine osteocytic (MLO-Y<sub>4</sub>)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 2%&#x2013;5%, 1&#x2013;20&#x2009;min</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Activation of ERK via integrin/cytoskeleton/Src-mediated signaling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plotkin et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr24-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse osteoblast (MC3T3-E1)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 3400 microstrain, 2&#x2009;Hz, 5&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased Wnt/B-catenin target genes (Wnt10B, SFRP1, cyclin D1, FZD2, WISP2, and connexin 43)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Robinson et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr25-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse osteoblast (MC3T3-E1)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 6%&#x2013;18% elongation, 24&#x2009;h, 0.1&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased OPG synthesis and decreased RANKL expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tang et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human osteosarcoma (MG63)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 10% elongation, 14&#x2009;h, 0.5&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain inhibited the promoter activation by vitamin D</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toyoshita et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr26-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat osteoblast</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation medium</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> &#x2212;2&#x2009;kPa, 1&#x2013;15&#x2009;days, 0.05&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nodule formation was enhanced, depending on the timing of initiation and magnitude of the deformation regimen</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Visconti et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SV40 human osteoblasts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation medium</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 0.8%&#x2013;3.2% elongation, 48&#x2009;h, 1&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-magnitude strain led to increased expression of OC, COL I and Cbfa1/Runx2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhu et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low-magnitude strain led to increased ALP activity</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="table-fn1-2041731415618342">
            <p>ERK: extracellular-regulated protein kinase; VEGF: vascular endothelial growth factor; bFGF: basic fibroblast growth factor; OCN: osteocalcin; OPN: osteopontin; FAK: focal adhesion kinase; NF-&#x3BA;B: nuclear factor-&#x3BA;B; TGF&#x3B2;1: transforming growth factor &#x3B2;1; COL: collagen; IGF1: insulin-like growth factor 1; IL: interleukin; PYK2: proline-rich tyrosine kinase 2; COX: cyclooxygenase; M-CSF: macrophage-colony stimulating factor; ALP: alkaline phosphatase; OPG: osteoprotegerin; MEK: mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK)-extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) kinase; RANKL: receptor activator of NF-kB ligand; OSX: osterix; RUNX2: Runt-related transcription factor 2; Egr-1: Early growth response protein 1; HIC5: hydrogen peroxide-inducible clone-5.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="table-fn2-2041731415618342">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>Flexercell model not specified.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <sec id="section3-2041731415618342">
        <title>Impact on cell survival, proliferation, and growth</title>
        <p>Tensile strain applied using the Flexercell increases osteoblast proliferation<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bibr20-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> although the magnitude of strain appears to have a bearing on the degree of proliferation that is permissible.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Application of a high strain level of 10%&#x2013;12% elongation at 0.1&#x2009;Hz for 24&#x2009;h stimulated proliferation in primary rat osteoblasts but the even greater mitogenic effect that transforming growth factor &#x3B2; (TGF&#x3B2;) has in the absence of strain was suppressed by strain itself,<sup><xref rid="bibr20-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> suggesting that mechanotransduction competes with TGF&#x3B2; signaling to dampen its effects. Application of mechanical strain to osteocytes and very mature osteoblasts failed to stimulate proliferation,<sup><xref rid="bibr29-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> and it was hence concluded that these cells respond differently to proliferative osteoblasts, instead regulating metabolic responses to strain reflective of their mechanosensing role in vivo.</p>
        <p>Lower levels of strain (2.5% elongation at 0.1&#x2009;Hz) were stimulatory to proliferation of human primary osteoblasts over 48&#x2009;h, without promoting alkaline phosphatase (ALP) activity or secretion of type I collagen or osteoprotegerin (OPG), suggesting that the cells were maintained in a premature state. However, pre-treating cells with testosterone prior to application of strain promoted osteogenic gene expression at the expense of proliferation,<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> highlighting that the effects of mechanotransduction are subject to a mechanistic switch regulated by androgens.</p>
        <p>A study assaying the effects of strain over a range of 0%&#x2013;9% elongation for 8&#x2009;h at 1&#x2009;Hz revealed that proliferation of normal human osteoblasts was magnitude dependent, with the highest strain producing the greatest level of proliferation.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Conditioned medium obtained from cultures stretched to 9% elongation stimulated cell proliferation in static culture, indicating the release of a soluble factor.</p>
        <p>In summary, the collated evidence indicates that stretch signals have a positive effect on osteoblast proliferation and they do so in a magnitude-dependent fashion. However, there will inevitably be a critical upper threshold at which stretch signals are no longer stimulatory to proliferation and are indeed detrimental to cell viability. Furthermore, biological molecules such as growth factors and hormones may alter the basal cell response to stretch, and this is particularly significant in vivo, where mechanical signals are just one of many facets of the cell microenvironment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section4-2041731415618342">
        <title>Matrix production</title>
        <p>When a range of stretch magnitudes from 0% to 9% was applied to human primary osteoblasts, expression of the type I collagen mRNA, COL1&#x3B1;II, was highest at 9% elongation, whereas in the case of mature osteoblast markers osteopontin (OPN) and osteocalcin (OCN), highest expression was seen at 3% strain, declining thereafter,<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> indicating a biphasic response to tensile strain. This parallels the authors&#x2019; observations for proliferation, which was superior at the highest magnitude of 9%. Furthermore, COL1 expression by human primary osteoblasts was only upregulated at a low magnitude of 2.5% strain in the presence of testosterone,<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> further evidence that the effect of mechanical stimulation is subject to hormonal influence. For type III collagen expression, where a &#x201C;high impact&#x201D; strain regime of between 5% and 12.5% strain at 0.5&#x2009;Hz for 24&#x2009;h on human osteosarcoma cells was used, Liu et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> found that COL3 mRNA was increased at 5% but then underwent a decline in the expression after 5%, whereas COL1 transcripts were stably increased at all strain levels compared to static control cultures. As type III collagen is normally deposited as an early wound matrix component, it is surprising that it was not increased at the higher strain level.</p>
        <p>In summary, early matrix production events, that is, deposition of type I collagenous material, appear to preferentially take place at higher strain levels in parallel with the enhanced proliferation effect. This may reflect the wound healing environment in vivo whereby early events of osteoblast proliferation and matrix deposition take place in a mechanically unstable environment prior to the formation of rigid bone, placing large amounts of strain on cells.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section5-2041731415618342">
        <title>Impact on cytokine/growth factor production</title>
        <p>Flexercell studies have revealed that numerous growth factors are upregulated in osteoblasts in response to stretch signals. Over a range of stretch from 0% to 9%, vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) expression by primary human osteoblasts was highest at 9% stretch.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> It also seems that the frequency with which stretch is applied influences the form of VEGF synthesized, as 1% stretch applied to both human and rat osteoblasts at various frequencies from 0.05 to 5&#x2009;Hz revealed that high-frequency stretch promoted the expression of VEGF isoforms that are matrix bound and low frequencies stimulated production of soluble VEGF isoforms.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Upregulation of VEGF, along with macrophage-colony stimulating factor (M-CSF) have been reported to be mechanistically important for the recruitment of osteoclasts in the remodeling of bone,<sup><xref rid="bibr22-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> and so stretch-induced VEGF expression is pivotal for the regulation of bone remodeling events in vivo as well as in revascularization of regenerating tissue.</p>
        <p>TGF&#x3B2; expression in human osteosarcoma cells was upregulated in response to mechanical stretch applied at 12% elongation.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> TGF&#x3B2; is a potent mitogen and can also promote collagen synthesis, both of which are important during the early stages of bone healing. However, binding of TGF&#x3B2; to the TGF&#x3B2; receptor-III is also enhanced by mechanical stretch,<sup><xref rid="bibr20-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> and this interaction has been shown to inhibit the ability of TGF&#x3B2; to activate osteoblasts.<sup><xref rid="bibr30-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="bibr31-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x2013;<xref rid="bibr32-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> Therefore, mechanical strain seems to finely regulate TGF&#x3B2; signaling and promote similar mitogenic and differentiation responses to TGF&#x3B2; but via a mechanotransduction pathway that competitively inhibits TGF&#x3B2; signaling.</p>
        <p>Mechanical stretch also enhanced osteoblastic expression of insulin-like growth factor (IGF) and basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF) at 12% maximal stretch at 3&#x2009;Hz, over a 24-h period.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Both factors stimulate early osteoblast healing responses such as osteoblast proliferation and matrix synthesis<sup><xref rid="bibr33-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="bibr34-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> and the early wound healing events induced in osteoblasts by high-magnitude stretch, such as proliferation and type I collagen expression (see above), may be a consequence of increased expression of these factors. Indeed, osteocytes, which act as mechanosensing cell in vivo, produce increasing levels of IGF in response to mechanical strain<sup><xref rid="bibr35-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><xref rid="bibr36-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x2013;<xref rid="bibr37-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> which may be one of the primary initiation events for the recruitment of osteoblast precursors during bone remodeling and regeneration.</p>
        <p>Increased expression of several bone morphogenetic proteins (BMPs), in particular BMP2, in response to low strain of 1% stretch was also reported in mouse osteoblastic MC3T3-E1 cells,<sup><xref rid="bibr38-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> yet in human primary osteoblasts subjected to stretch over a range of 0%&#x2013;9% elongation, increased gene expression was only seen at 6% and above.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> However, the overall positive effect of mechanical stretch on osteoblastic expression of BMP2 is further evidence of the stimulatory effect of mechanical stretch signals on osteogenesis.</p>
        <p>In terms of the bone remodeling balance, mechanical stretch also seems to have a role in regulation of bone resorption by osteoclasts. Interleukin 6 (IL6) has a well-known role in osteoclast production during normal bone homeostasis.<sup><xref rid="bibr39-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> Increased expression of IL6 was observed in human osteosarcoma cells stretched at 12% elongation at 0.05&#x2009;Hz<sup><xref rid="bibr12-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> and in human primary osteoblasts stretched at 2.5% elongation at 0.1&#x2009;Hz.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> In the latter study, OPG, an inhibitor of osteoclastogenesis, was produced when stretch was applied in combination with testosterone, but not in its absence, demonstrating the coordinated action of mechanotransduction and hormones. The effects of stretch on IL6 are magnitude dependent, as studies of mouse MC3T3-E1 osteoblastic cells exposed to a regime of 0%&#x2013;9% elongation revealed that the greatest level of IL6 production was seen at 9% stretch and was dependent on prostaglandin E2 production by cyclooxygenase 2.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup></p>
        <p>A key downstream consequence of IL6 activity in osteoblasts that leads to osteoclast activation is production of RANKL.<sup><xref rid="bibr39-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> There is some debate in the literature about the effect of mechanical strain on RANKL expression. Some researchers have reported a magnitude-dependent decline in RANKL expression,<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr13-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> and this was accompanied by an increase in the expression of the transcription factors Osterix and Runx2<sup><xref rid="bibr13-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> and OPG.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> However, Kim et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> reported an increase in RANKL expression after exposure to mechanical strain. Nevertheless, in this study, a potential mechanism for preventing osteoclast activity in order to maintain an osteoanabolic process was discovered using MC3T3-E1 cells transfected with RANKL cDNA. The expression of RANKL increased in transfected cells, but when low-level mechanical strain was applied daily for 1&#x2009;week, most of the protein was in membrane-bound form with a large reduction in soluble RANKL, thus reducing its bioavailability.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> In any case, RAW264.7 cells that are capable of osteoclastic differentiation in the presence of RANKL failed to do so effectively in the presence of mechanical strain of 10% elongation at 0.5&#x2009;Hz over 1&#x2009;week.<sup><xref rid="bibr40-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> Together with the strong hormonal influence as demonstrated for testosterone,<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> osteoclast activity is subject to further regulation upon exposure to strain.</p>
        <p>Overall, mechanical stretch signals induce the expression of factors that invoke early wound healing events such as mesenchymal cell proliferation and angiogenesis. Furthermore, stretch-induced upregulation of factors such as VEGF and IL6 results in osteoclast recruitment and differentiation, which is in turn carefully regulated by androgens. Studies that have assayed growth factor production over a range of different elongations generally concur that growth factor production is magnitude dependent. This likely reflects the early wound healing response where the fracture site is highly unstable and growth factors are in abundance.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section6-2041731415618342">
        <title>Cellular maturation and differentiation</title>
        <p>Osteoblastic differentiation, maturation, and ultimately mineralized matrix deposition can be directly enhanced by mechanical strain applied using Flexercell. For example, stretch applied to immortalized mouse calvarial osteoblasts overnight at 2% elongation enhanced the expression of osteogenic transcription factors, osterix and runx2.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Over a range of elongations from 0% to 3.2%, a subsequent study found that runx2 was significantly upregulated only at 3.2% stretch but not at 2.4% or lower, and type I collagen expression was upregulated in proportion to magnitude of stretch.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> In this study, OCN was only upregulated at 2.4%&#x2013;3.2% elongation, whereas ALP (expressed earlier in osteogenic differentiation) was upregulated at 0.8%&#x2013;1.6% elongation but not above.</p>
        <p>The strain magnitude-dependent expression of OCN by human primary osteoblasts was further confirmed using an elongation range of 0%&#x2013;9%. OCN expression was upregulated at 3%, 6%, and 9% elongation compared to 0% control cultures,<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> whereas in the case of osteonectin and OPN, greatest gene expression was seen at 3% and then underwent a gradual decline in basal levels by 9%.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> At stretch magnitude as low as 1% elongation, bone nodule formation was induced in monolayers of mouse MC3T3-E1 and rat primary osteoblasts.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="bibr41-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> Particularly intriguing is the fact that some researchers reported that early osteogenic events such as proliferation and collagen production were best at a high strain of 9%, whereas the expression of differentiation markers OPN and OCN was most favorable at low strain of 3% elongation,<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> and bone nodule formation was reported as low as 1% elongation.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="bibr41-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> Other researchers reported that the osteoanabolic phenotype was enhanced in osteoblasts with increasing magnitude of strain up to 18% elongation, characterized by enhanced expression of OPG,<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> which is a potent inhibitor of osteoclast formation and activity.<sup><xref rid="bibr42-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> However, it is not just the magnitude of strain that impacts the specific response of osteoblasts but the timing of application and duration of strain that determine the exact nature of cell responses. According to the work of Visconti et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr27-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> applying strain after a prolonged static culture period (either 3 or 10&#x2009;days) produced a greater number of bone nodules than applying strain after just 1&#x2009;day of static culture. This suggests that a regime that promotes mineralized matrix formation should be applied after early events such as collagen matrix deposition have been given time to occur.</p>
        <p>To summarize the impact of mechanical stretch on osteogenic differentiation and maturation, it is clear that lower magnitude strain in the region of &lt;5% elongation is superior for directing these events, a contrast to early events such as proliferation and type I collagen production, which are optimally enhanced at greater magnitudes of stretch (around 9% elongation).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section7-2041731415618342">
      <title>Effect of mechanical strain on skeletal muscle cells</title>
      <p>Mechanical strain is transmitted through tendons and ligaments during locomotion, when muscle contraction occurs. Skeletal muscle itself generates contractile forces that are propagated through the muscle fiber network. The nature of force generation in skeletal muscle means that as well as contraction, cells experience stretch stimuli.</p>
      <p>In order to fully critically appraise the information in this area, a brief description of how skeletal muscle differentiates and regenerates is appropriate. The tissue itself is characterized by multinucleate muscle fibers encapsulated by connective tissue, mainly collagen, fixed at both ends (junctions).</p>
      <p>In terms of mechano-responsiveness, it could be suggested that skeletal muscle is the most relevant tissue in the human body. It is composed of elongated multinucleate muscle fibers that develop from the &#x201C;end-to-end&#x201D; fusing of mononuclear muscle precursor cells (MPCs) in a process known as differentiation. In development, these mononuclear cells are derived from the somites and, depending upon the anatomical location, the MPCs either migrate to differentiate at their final destination, for example, limb muscle or differentiate at or near their final destination, for example, head and neck muscles. However and astoundingly, skeletal muscle is a not a solely post-mitotic tissue. MPCs located in the periphery of post-natal muscle fibers can become activated by a variety of stimuli including mechanical. This activation triggers a series of events that lead to the asymmetric division of these cells. This process can be recapitulated with in vitro cell culture and is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2041731415618342">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
      <fig id="fig2-2041731415618342" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A series of processes from MPCs to differentiated myotubes.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2041731415618342-fig2"/>
      </fig>
      <p>It is therefore very important to understand at which part of the process the cells are being stimulated using the Flexercell apparatus where a large number of studies have demonstrated that mechanical strain activates muscle cells at different stages of maturity from skeletal myoblasts to satellite cells,<sup><xref rid="bibr43-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">43</xref><xref rid="bibr44-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr45-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr46-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x2013;<xref rid="bibr47-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> and a summary of muscle cell studies is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-2041731415618342">Table 2</xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="table2-2041731415618342" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summary of Flexercell studies and key findings using muscle cells.</p>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2041731415618342-table2"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell type</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage of differentiation</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch device and regime</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key findings</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Proliferating MPCs</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent/early fusion</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, cyclical stretch at 3% at 0.05&#x2009;Hz for 24&#x2013;72&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased MyoD, MyoG, Mef2, MHC</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bruce et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr48-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch abrogated the reductions in the expression of the above by TNF&#x3B1; treatment</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12)</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Single cells; 24-h post-plating</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 15% strain, 0.5&#x2009;Hz, cyclical for up to 48&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased proliferation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iwanuma et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr47-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased IGF1 and caspase mRNA expression in the initial 24&#x2009;h of stretch</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDC</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 15% strain for 10&#x2009;min</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overexpression of REDD2 inhibits response of mTOR to mechanical stimulation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miyazaki and Esser<sup><xref rid="bibr49-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;95% desmin-positive single MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 12&#x2013;36&#x2009;h post-plating at 25% strain for 12&#x2013;36&#x2009;h with 12-s intervals</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in BrdU&#x2009;+&#x2009;cells after 12-h stretch</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tatsumi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr43-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in HGF in CM at 12&#x2009;h. Anti-HGF antibody prevents increase in BrdU&#x2009;+&#x2009;cells. Stretch releases pre-existing HGF from ECM</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;95% Desmin positive single MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 12&#x2013;36&#x2009;h post-plating at 25% strain for 24&#x2009;h with 12&#x2009;s intervals</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in LH limb BrdU&#x2009;+&#x2009;cells compared to BK and UH cultures following stretch. Increase in HGF in CM of LH cultures stretch compared to BK and UH</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tatsumi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr50-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;95% desmin-positive single MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 12&#x2013;36&#x2009;h post-plating at 25% strain for 24&#x2009;h with 12-s intervals</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in BrdU&#x2009;+&#x2009;cells at an optimal pH (7.2)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tatsumi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr44-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in BrdU&#x2009;+&#x2009;cells in a HGF- and NO-dependent mechanism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 12&#x2013;36&#x2009;h post-plating at 25% strain for 24&#x2009;h with 12-s intervals</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch activation of BrdU&#x2009;+&#x2009;cells is NO dependent</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tatsumi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr45-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 25% strain, 12-s intervals for 2&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch induced an increase in the active form of MMP2 in a NO-dependent mechanism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yamada et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr51-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Aligning MPCs</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12) and murine MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Single cells induced to differentiate; 24-h post-seeding (C2C12) or immediately post-seeding (MDCs)</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 48&#x2009;h uniaxial ramp stretch, followed by intermittent strain at 2%&#x2013;6% strain for 4&#x2009;days. Cyclic stretch at 1&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2D: reductions in MRF-4 and MYH-4 mRNA in both cell types. Increase in MYH-1 mRNA (C2C12 only)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boonen et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr52-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3D: reductions in MRFs, MyoD, myogenin (both cell types) MRF-4 (C2C12) and MLP (MDCs). Increases in actin and &#x3B1;-actinin mRNA at day 4 (C2C12), reduction in MYH mRNAs (both cell types)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cells induced to differentiate</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 17% cyclical stretch, 1&#x2009;Hz for 1&#x2009;h every 24&#x2009;h for 5&#x2009;days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch increased proliferation and inhibited differentiation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kumar et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr53-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cells induced to differentiate</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 15% cyclical strain for up to 5&#x2009;days at 0.1, 0.5, and 0.9&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch improved proliferation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kurokawa et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr54-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch led to increased MHC-perinatal expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast stretch led to early expression, slow led to later expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat myoblasts (L6)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cells induced to differentiate</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 20% cyclical strain at 0.5&#x2009;Hz for up to 24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch caused caspase-induced apoptosis during differentiation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liu et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr55-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine MDCs isolated from WT and <italic>mdx</italic> tissue</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#x2009;h in differentiation medium (early differentiation)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 10% strain for 2&#x2009;s, followed by 20&#x2013;60&#x2009;s in the non-stretched position</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in real time measurement of NO production during stretch (WT). No observed increase in NO in <italic>mdx</italic> MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wozniak and Anderson<sup><xref rid="bibr56-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1&#x2013;P2 rat MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 25% strain at 6 cycles/min, each cycle consisting of 3-s strain, 3-s rest. Continuous for 24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch induced an increase in Na<sup>+</sup> pump activity, increased expression of &#x3B1;-2 subunit of Na<sup>+</sup>-K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase in the membrane fractions. Mediated through PI3-K</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yuan et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr57-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cells induced to differentiate</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 10% strain at 0.5&#x2009;Hz for 1&#x2009;h on, 5&#x2009;h off-0-4&#x2009;days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in actin fiber formation, myotube maturation (increase in &#x3B1;-actinin and striations) and myotube diameter with stretch. &#x3B2;<sub>1D</sub> and FAK proposed mediated mechanism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhang et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr58-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>Myotubes</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat myoblasts (L6)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myotubes (7&#x2013;9&#x2009;days in culture)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 1&#x2009;Hz at 15% strain at 2, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, and 150&#x2009;min</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sarcoplasmic protein synthesis was unaltered; however, myofibrillar protein synthesis was decreased. Paradoxically, anabolic signaling (phosphorylation of key proteins) was enhanced</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atherton et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr59-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Stretched during differentiation or 10-min stretch after 7-day differentiation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, cyclical strain during differentiation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretching during differentiation increase CK activity</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clarke and Feeback<sup><xref rid="bibr60-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10%&#x2013;20% cyclical strain</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acute stretching caused membrane wounding and FGF release</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse diaphragm MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myotubes (5&#x2009;days in DM)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 4&#x2009;h, 10% stretch, 1.5&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No effect of stretch on proinflammatory marker gene expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demoule et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr61-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat myoblasts (L6)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myotubes (7&#x2009;days in DM)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 10% stretch, 4&#x2009;h, 1.5&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mechanical stretch plus oxidative stress (induced by SIN-1) causes sarcolemmal injury to a greater extent than either component alone</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ebihara et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr62-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat myoblasts (L6)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early myotubes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 96&#x2009;h of cyclical strain (18% stretch, 0.16&#x2009;Hz) +/&#x2212; heat stress</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total protein, HSP72 and 90 protein concentrations were increased by stretch and heat in a cumulative manner</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goto et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr63-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myotubes (5&#x2013;6&#x2009;days post-induction of differentiation)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 15% stretch, 1&#x2009;Hz, 10&#x2009;min, cyclical</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased phosphorylation of p70s6k following multiaxial versus uniaxial</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hornberger et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr64-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myotubes (5&#x2013;6&#x2009;days post-induction of differentiation)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 15% stretch, 1&#x2009;Hz, 10&#x2009;min, cyclical</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch caused phosphorylation of p70s6k</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hornberger<sup><xref rid="bibr65-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Addition of locally acting growth factors to myotubes did not have the same effect</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early myotubes (8&#x2013;10&#x2009;days post initial plating)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, up to 24&#x2009;h cyclical stretch, 0.25&#x2009;Hz, 24% strain</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#x2009;h stretching increased Ach esterase activity</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hubatsch and Jasmin<sup><xref rid="bibr66-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat myoblasts (L6)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myotubes; 7&#x2013;8&#x2009;days post-plating and in DM</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 100C, 25% cyclical stretch at 0.5&#x2009;Hz for up to 48&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch caused increased glucose uptake in myotubes, not myoblasts independent of GLUT1 and 4 receptor content</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitsumoto and Klip<sup><xref rid="bibr67-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine myoblast (C2C12)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early myotubes (24-h DM)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 1&#x2009;Hz, 20% strain consitisting of 20&#x2009;s on, 20&#x2009;s off. Continuous for 24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase LDH into CM. Neutrophil cytotoxicity of muscle cell membrane mediated by MPO</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nguyen et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr68-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myotubes (5&#x2009;days in DM)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 0.25&#x2009;Hz at 1.5, 4.9, 9.5, and 15% strains, for 30&#x2009;min, 2&#x2009;s on, 2&#x2009;s off</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased injury index and neutrophil chemotaxis with increased strain. Increases in IL8 and MCP-1 in conditioned media</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peterson and Pizza<sup><xref rid="bibr69-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat myoblasts (L6) and rat MDC-sarcoglycan (SG) deficient</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myotubes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 20% strain at 6 cycles/min for 1&#x2009;h. Bioflex plates also used for microscopy</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in creatine phosphokinase in CM following stretch. Stretch-induced damage in SG-deficient cells caused by alteration in Ca<sup>2+</sup> dynamics</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampaolesi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr70-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human MDCs</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myotubes (5&#x2009;days in DM)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 0.25&#x2009;Hz for 2&#x2009;h at 5%, 10%, 20%, or 30% strain</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower myotube injury index at lower strains compared to higher strains and scrape injury (based on LDH in CM). Evidence for membrane rupture and an increase in lanthanum-rimmed membrane blebs (sign of injury) at 30% strain. Increased chemotaxis index of neutrophils using CM at higher strains</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tsivitse et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr71-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="table-fn3-2041731415618342">
            <p>Mef2: mouse embryonic fibroblasts 2; MHC: myosin heavy chain; TNF&#x3B1;: tumor necrosis factor &#x3B1;; IGF1: insulin-like growth factor 1; MDC: myeloid-derived suppressor cell; mTOR: mammalian target of rapamycin; BrdU: bromodeoxyuridine; HGF: hepatocyte growth factor; CM: conditioned media; ECM: extracellular matrix; NO: nitric oxide; MMP2: matrix metallopeptidase 2; 2D: two-dimensional; MRF: myogenic regulatory factor; 3D: three-dimensional; PI3-K: phosphoinositide 3-kinase; FAK: focal adhesion kinase; CK: creatine kinase; FGF: fibroblast growth factor; GLUT1 and 4: glucose transporters 1 and 4; LDH: lactate dehydrogenase; IL8: interleukin 8; MCP-1: monocyte chemoattractant protein-1; MyoG: myogenin; REDD2: regulated in development and DNA damage responses 2; MYH: myosin, heavy chain; MLP: muscle LIM protein; WT: normal C57BL/6 wild-type; SIN-1: 3-morpholinosydnonimine-N-ethylcarbamide; HSP72: heat shock proteins; LH: lower hind; BK: back; UH: upper hind; Ach: acetylcholinesterase; MPO: myeloperoxidase.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="table-fn4-2041731415618342">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>Flexercell model not specified.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <sec id="section8-2041731415618342">
        <title>Impact on cell survival, proliferation, and growth</title>
        <p>In the vast majority of studies, it is striking that cyclic stretching of single MPCs upregulates both proliferation and expression of genes and proteins that are required for further differentiation: MYOD1, myogenin (MYOG), MEF2A, p21 (CDKN1A), and IGF1.<sup><xref rid="bibr47-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> Furthermore, several genes encoding muscle structural proteins are upregulated, including myosin heavy chain (MyHC) isoforms and &#x3B1;-tropomyosin (TPM1), and this ultimately leads to increased myotube production.<sup><xref rid="bibr46-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> Intriguingly, differences in stretch-induced satellite cell responses have been reported from muscles isolated from distinct anatomical regions that contain primarily fast-twitch or slow-twitch fibers.<sup><xref rid="bibr50-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> Further evidence of stretch favorably enhancing cell growth, tissue building, and regeneration includes an increase in total protein levels in response to mechanical stretch,<sup><xref rid="bibr63-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup> and the whole process of stretch-induced cell growth is dependent on mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) activation.<sup><xref rid="bibr72-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup> However, an antagonist, REDD2, is also expressed in skeletal muscle and is capable of inhibiting stretch-activated mTOR activity.<sup><xref rid="bibr49-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> Nitric oxide synthase (NOS) becomes upregulated<sup><xref rid="bibr46-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> and bFGF expression is increased, also in a strain-dependent fashion.<sup><xref rid="bibr60-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> NOS drives the synthesis and release of nitric oxide (NO) from mature muscle myotubes.<sup><xref rid="bibr56-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> Together with FGF, NO has well-known mitogenic potential and initiates a &#x201C;wound healing&#x201D; response. It does this, at least in part, by activation of satellite cells via matrix metallopeptidase 2 (MMP2)-mediated release of hepatocyte growth factor (HGF) from ECM<sup><xref rid="bibr51-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> and subsequently leads to HGF signaling.<sup><xref rid="bibr43-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">43</xref><xref rid="bibr44-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x2013;<xref rid="bibr45-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="bibr73-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,<xref rid="bibr74-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></sup> It is particularly noteworthy that single MPCs are very tolerant of a wide range of strain with values ranging from 2% to 25% eliciting similar (sometimes with a dose response) effect.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section9-2041731415618342">
        <title>Impact on the differentiation process and differentiated cells (myotubes)</title>
        <p>As MPCs are &#x201C;preparing&#x201D; to fuse into multinucleate myotubes, their sensitivity to strain appears to increase<sup><xref rid="bibr75-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></sup> although the global responses remain fairly similar&#x2014;including increased proliferation rates and increased indicators of fusion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-2041731415618342">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>In stark contrast to the data seen with single cells, MPCs fused into myotubes respond in quite different ways. One of the most striking observations is that &#x201C;tolerance&#x201D; to varying strain rates is lost. Rates nearing in excess of 20% elicited a variety of deleterious effects such as increased creatine kinase (CK) and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) activity,<sup><xref rid="bibr60-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="bibr68-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,<xref rid="bibr70-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,<xref rid="bibr71-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup> membrane wounding and cell &#x201C;injury,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="bibr60-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="bibr71-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,<xref rid="bibr76-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></sup> inflammatory cytokine and wound repair growth factor release,<sup><xref rid="bibr60-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="bibr76-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></sup> sarcolemmal disruption,<sup><xref rid="bibr62-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup> increases in molecular chaperonins,<sup><xref rid="bibr63-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup> and increased acetylcholinesterase production.<sup><xref rid="bibr66-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup> Overall, stretching myotubes appeared to have no real effect on parameters related to cell proliferation and differentiation; however, there is some evidence of changes to cellular metabolism such as increased glucose uptake<sup><xref rid="bibr67-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></sup> and phosphorylation of a number of anabolic targets such as ribosomal S6 kinase P70S6K<sup><xref rid="bibr59-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="bibr72-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup>, focal adhesion kinase (FAK), protein kinase B (Akt), 4E binding protein 1 (4EBP1), eukaryotic elongation factor 2 (eEF2), extracellular-regulated protein kinase 1/2 (ERK1/2), eukaryotic initiation factor 2&#x3B1; (eIF2&#x3B1;), and eukaryotic initiation factor 4E (eIF4).<sup><xref rid="bibr59-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> Notably, however, myofibrillar protein synthesis was actually suppressed.<sup><xref rid="bibr59-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup></p>
        <p>In conclusion, there is a good deal of data that have been collected, and the system has, for skeletal muscle, some utility for single MPCs work concentrating on some aspects of cellular signaling. There are clearly wider considerations when it comes to interpretation of the myotube data and also around the biomimetic nature of the systems and the interplay with other cell types.<sup><xref rid="bibr77-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></sup> The most powerful use is for comparing the same conditions across varying cell types, as described in this review.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section10-2041731415618342">
      <title>Effect of mechanical strain on tendon and ligament cells</title>
      <p>Tendon and ligament are important connective tissues, essential for healthy musculoskeletal physiology. Ligaments bind skeletal components together, maintaining their correct anatomical arrangement. Tendons connect muscles to bone and facilitate the transmission of contractile force from those muscles to control movement. They are therefore able to withstand high mechanical strain during normal physiological conditions. However, chronic overuse or pathologically high magnitudes of strain result in damage, causing considerable pain and impaired mobility. Using the Flexercell system, the effect of mechanical strain on cellular constituents of tendons and ligaments can be studied, facilitating our understanding of how these tissues respond to, and propagate, mechanical signals (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-2041731415618342">Table 3</xref>). This in turn may help us to understand the kind of mechanical stimulation appropriate for engineering replacement tissues.</p>
      <table-wrap id="table3-2041731415618342" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summary of Flexercell studies and key findings using ligament cells.</p>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2041731415618342-table3"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell type</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage of differentiation</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch device and regime</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key findings</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> TENS-L (3%, 6%, 8%), TENS-H (15%), 30&#x2013;120&#x2009;min</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suppressed IL1&#x3B2;-induced COX2 expression TENS-H upregulated COX2 expression and PGE<sub>2</sub> synthesis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agarwal et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr78-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 20&#x2009;kPa, 12&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased expression of MMP1, MMP2, TIMP1, TIMP2, &#x3B1;6 and &#x3B2;1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bolcato-Bellemin et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr79-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 15% 30 cycles/min consisting of 1&#x2009;s strain, 1&#x2009;s rest</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreased ALP activity</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chiba and Mitani<sup><xref rid="bibr80-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">80</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Canine ACL and MCL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 5% (0.05 strain) strain at 6 cycles/min for 2 or 22&#x2009;h daily for 3&#x2009;days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased &#x3B1;5 and &#x3B2;1 expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hannafin et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr81-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased &#x3B2;3 expression when cells grown on laminin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canine ACL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 5%&#x2013;15% strain at 6 cycles/min for 2&#x2009;h followed by 22-h rest for 5 consecutive days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased &#x3B1;5 and &#x3B2;1 expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Henshaw et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr82-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">82</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 9% strain at 6 cycles/min consisting of 5&#x2009;s strain, 5&#x2009;s for 6&#x2009;days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased UNCL expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr83-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">83</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 5% elongation, 3 cycles/min for 24&#x2009;h on 7&#x2009;days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased TGF&#x3B2;1 levels</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kimoto et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr84-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreased M-CSF expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Canine ACL and MCL</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Confluent single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 60 cycles/min with 0.05&#x2013;0.075 strain for 0.5&#x2013;24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACL: Increased COL I</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsieh et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr85-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCL: Increased COL III</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat MCL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 3.5% elongation, 2&#x2009;h, 1&#x2009;Hz, microgrooved substrate</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased sensitivity to load and ability to propagate a calcium wave</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jones et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr86-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">86</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoblast-like characteristics</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 6%&#x2013;15%, 0.005&#x2009;Hz, 24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low-magnitude strain inhibited IL1&#x3B2;-induced synthesis of IL11, IL6, and IL8 and induced IL10 synthesis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr87-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">87</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent single cells</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 9%&#x2013;18% strain for 6 cycles/min consisting of 5&#x2009;s strain, 5&#x2009;s rest, 1&#x2013;5&#x2009;days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased ALP and OCN expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matsuda et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr88-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">88</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EGF/EGF-R system acts as a negative regulator of differentiation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human LFC</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 10%&#x2013;20% strain, 0.16&#x2009;Hz, 24&#x2013;48&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased COL I, III, and V via TGF&#x3B2;1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nakatani et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr89-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">89</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bovine PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bioflex loading stations, 0.2%&#x2013;18% stretch for 6 cycles/min consisting of 5&#x2009;s strain, 5&#x2009;s rest, 48&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-magnitude strain increased COL I and decorin expression but decreased ALP</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ozaki et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr90-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">90</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 18% stretch for 6 cycles/min consisting of 5&#x2009;s strain, 5&#x2009;s rest, 1&#x2013;5&#x2009;days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased activity of plasminogen activator</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ozawa et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr91-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">91</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat PDL (6-week young rats and 60-week old rats)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 9%&#x2013;18% stretch for 6 cycles/min consisting of 5&#x2009;s strain, 5&#x2009;s rest, 1&#x2013;5&#x2009;days</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased PGE<sub>2</sub> and IL1&#x3B2; production by old versus young in response to strain</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shimizu et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr92-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 15% stretch for 30 cycles/min consisting of 1&#x2009;s strain, 1&#x2009;s rest, 30&#x2013;90&#x2009;min and 6&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rapid, transient increase in C-FOS expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yamaguchi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr93-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">93</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No change in expression of osteogenic genes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 12% for 6&#x2009;s every 90&#x2009;s, 6, 12, and 24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased expression of BMP2, BMP6, ALP, SOX9, MSX1, and VEGFA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wescott et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr94-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreased expression of BMP4 and EGF</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human PDL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 7%&#x2013;21% stretch for 12 cycles/min consisting 2.5&#x2009;s strain, 2.5&#x2009;s rest, 24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased VEGF expression and secretion</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yoshino et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr95-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">95</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="table-fn5-2041731415618342">
            <p>PDL: periodontal ligament; IL: interleukin; COX2: cyclooxygenase 2; PGE<sub>2</sub>: prostaglandin E2; MMP: matrix metallopeptidase; TIMP: tissue inhibitors of metalloproteinases; ALP: alkaline phosphatase; ACL: anterior cruciate ligament; MCL: medial collateral ligament; UNCL: ulnar collateral ligament; TGF&#x3B2;1: transforming growth factor &#x3B2;1; M-CSF: macrophage-colony stimulating factor; OCN: osteocalcin; EGF: epidermal growth factor; EGF-R: epidermal growth factor receptor; BMP: bone morphogenetic protein; VEGFA: vascular endothelial growth factor A; TENS-L: tensile strain of low magnitude; TENS-H: tensile strain of high magnitude; LFC: Ligamenturn flavum cells; C-FOS: FBJ murine osteosarcoma viral oncogene; SOX9: SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 9; MSX1: Msh homeobox 1.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="table-fn6-2041731415618342">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>Flexercell model not specified.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <sec id="section11-2041731415618342">
        <title>Impact on cell survival, proliferation, and growth</title>
        <p>One of the earliest studies using Flexercell demonstrated that applied cyclic stretch alone was not capable of increasing flexor tendon proliferation, but when applied in combination with platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF), or a cocktail containing both PDGF and IGF, synthesis of DNA was significantly enhanced.<sup><xref rid="bibr96-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">96</xref></sup> This could be prevented by blocking gap junction activity with the gap junction inhibitor octanol, indicating the importance of cell&#x2013;cell communication for cell proliferation.<sup><xref rid="bibr97-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">97</xref></sup> Therefore, in terms of proliferation, fibroblastic cells appear not to respond as favorably to mechanical stretch signals as osteoblasts or MPCs. For tissue engineering purposes, it will be necessary to screen the appropriate combination of mechanical stretch and growth factors to create functional tendon tissue with appropriate cell number or seed the scaffold with the desired number of cells required to form mature tissue at the outset.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section12-2041731415618342">
        <title>Matrix production</title>
        <p>Mechanical stretch has been widely reported to upregulate type I collagen synthesis by tendon cells<sup><xref rid="bibr97-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,<xref rid="bibr98-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></sup> and ligament cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr85-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,<xref rid="bibr89-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,<xref rid="bibr90-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,<xref rid="bibr99-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">99</xref></sup> Curiously in the case of the knee joint, type I collagen is upregulated by fibroblasts of the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL)<sup><xref rid="bibr85-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,<xref rid="bibr99-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">99</xref></sup> but not those from the medial collateral ligament (MCL).<sup><xref rid="bibr85-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></sup> Conversely, type III collagen is upregulated upon application of strain in MCL cells, but not ACL.<sup><xref rid="bibr85-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,<xref rid="bibr99-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">99</xref></sup> These differences in collagen expression profiles might explain differences in healing of ACL versus MCL evident in vivo, with lack of healing in ACL due to lack of type III collagen production.<sup><xref rid="bibr85-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></sup> They also deliver a resounding reminder that seemingly comparable cell populations from different topographic sites can behave rather differently to each other, as demonstrated with topographically distinct skin fibroblast populations that have distinct phenotype and gene expression profiles.<sup><xref rid="bibr100-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">100</xref><xref rid="bibr101-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x2013;<xref rid="bibr102-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">102</xref></sup></p>
        <p>In fibroblasts from ligamentum flavum, mechanical stretch induces the expression of collagen types I, III, and V via a TGF&#x3B2;-dependent mechanism.<sup><xref rid="bibr89-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">89</xref></sup> In static culture, estrogen increases the expression of collagen types I and III,<sup><xref rid="bibr99-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,<xref rid="bibr103-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">103</xref></sup> but combined with mechanical stretch signals, actually reduces their expression, along with biglycan.<sup><xref rid="bibr99-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,<xref rid="bibr103-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">103</xref></sup> The compound effect of stretch and estrogen might account for the up to eightfold increase in risk of ACL injury in female athletes.<sup><xref rid="bibr104-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">104</xref><xref rid="bibr105-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x2013;<xref rid="bibr106-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">106</xref></sup></p>
        <p>Aside from synthesis of matrix components, it is important to have a controlled balance between proteases that degrade ECM proteins and their inhibitors during matrix turnover and remodeling, and a number of different proteases are upregulated in periodontal ligament (PDL) fibroblasts upon mechanical stimulation. For example, plasminogen activator (PA) is upregulated in mechanically stretched PDL cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr91-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,<xref rid="bibr107-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">107</xref></sup> PA is a wide-spectrum serine protease that activates plasminogen to produce plasmin, which in turn activates MMPs to degrade ECM components and cell adhesion molecules,<sup><xref rid="bibr108-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">108</xref></sup> important events during matrix remodeling, cell mobilization, and differentiation. Furthermore, transcript levels of MMPs themselves (MMP1 and MMP2), along with their inhibitors (tissue inhibitors of metalloproteinase 1 and 2 (TIMP1 and TIMP2)) are upregulated relative to unstretched controls,<sup><xref rid="bibr79-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></sup> again indicating that mechanical stimulation enhances matrix remodeling, which is essential for maintaining structural integrity and strength in ligament tissue in vivo. It has also been reported that cell aging leads to increased PA activity,<sup><xref rid="bibr109-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">109</xref></sup> which may reflect the impaired healing capacity that is typically seen in aged individuals.</p>
        <p>Exposing tendon cells to IL1 decreased their elastic modulus, thereby increasing their survival after exposure to high-magnitude stretch in 3D collagen gels (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-2041731415618342">Table 4</xref>).<sup><xref rid="bibr115-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">115</xref></sup> Coupled with this, IL1 enhanced elastin expression but suppressed type I collagen expression by tendon cells cultured within the constructs,<sup><xref rid="bibr114-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">114</xref></sup> which will have a bearing on the mechanical properties of bioengineered constructs that are produced this way. Therefore, a potential means of tuning the mechanical properties of engineered tendon tissues for regenerative therapy may be achievable via regulation not just of the biomaterial substrate but also of the tendon cells themselves.</p>
        <table-wrap id="table4-2041731415618342" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Summary of Flexercell studies and key findings using tendon cells.</p>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2041731415618342-table4"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell type</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage of differentiation</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch device and regime</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key findings</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabbit Achilles tendon</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenocytes</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 5% elongation, 0.33&#x2009;Hz for 6&#x2009;h with 18&#x2009;h of rest</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Synergistic effect of strain and IL1&#x3B2; to upregulate the production of stromelysin pro-enzyme</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Archambault et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr110-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">110</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain alone induced no effect</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canine patellar tendon</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenocytes</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 1%&#x2013;9% strain, 0.5&#x2013;3.0&#x2009;Hz, 15&#x2013;120&#x2009;min</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transient JNK activation peaking at 30&#x2009;min and returning to basal levels by 2&#x2009;h</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arnoczky et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr111-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">111</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avian flexor tendon</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epitenon and tendon internal fibroblasts</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 5% elongation, 1&#x2009;Hz for 8&#x2009;h</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain stimulates proliferation in the presence of PDGF-BB and IGF1 and promotes phosphorylation in multiple proteins</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Banes et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr96-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">96</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avian flexor tendon</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenocytes</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 0.65%, 1&#x2009;Hz, 8&#x2009;h/day, 16-h rest</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Induced expression of numerous novel genes</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Banes et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr112-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">112</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Porcine posterior tibial tendon</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenocytes</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 5% strain, 0.5&#x2009;Hz for 24&#x2009;h</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased COL I and decorin gene expression</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr98-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human tenosynovial fibroblasts</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenosynovial fibroblasts</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 20%, 1&#x2009;Hz, 36&#x2009;h</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased expression of PGE<sub>2</sub> and VEGF</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hirata et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr113-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">113</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human tendon</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tendon internal fibroblasts forming bioartificial tendons</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 30% strain for 10&#x2009;s</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL1&#x3B2; low dose upregulated elastin expression and high dose suppressed COL I expression to increase elasticity and prevent rupture due to strain</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr114-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">114</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human tendon</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tendon internal fibroblasts forming bioartificial tendons</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 3.5% elongation, 1&#x2009;Hz, for 1&#x2009;h/day</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL1&#x3B2; reduced Young&#x2019;s modulus in bioartificial tendons, increasing their tolerance to mechanical strain</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr115-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">115</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avian flexor tendons</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenocytes</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 75 millistrain at 1&#x2009;Hz in a regime of 8&#x2009;h on, 16&#x2009;h resting, for 96&#x2009;h</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased junctional components n-cadherin and vinculin, but no change in actin levels</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ralphs et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr116-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">116</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human flexor tendons</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenocytes</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 3.5% strain at 1&#x2009;Hz for 5&#x2013;30&#x2009;min and 1&#x2013;2&#x2009;h</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stimulation of ecto-ATP activity</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tsuzaki et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr117-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">117</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human flexor tendons</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenocytes</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 3.5% strain at 1&#x2009;Hz for 2-h and 18-h rest</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Induced IL1&#x3B2;, COX2 and MMP3, but not MMP1</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tsuzaki et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr117-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">117</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP modulated stretch-induced gene expression</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human flexor tendons</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tendon internal fibroblasts</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 3%&#x2013;5% strain at 1&#x2009;Hz for 1&#x2013;6&#x2009;h</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Connexin 43 colocalization with actin increased with strain</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wall et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr118-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">118</xref></sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="table-fn7-2041731415618342">
              <p>IL1&#x3B2;: interleukin 1&#x3B2;; PDGF-BB: platelet-derived growth factor-BB; IGF1: insulin-like growth factor 1; PGE<sub>2</sub>: prostaglandin E2; VEGF: vascular endothelial growth factor; COX2: cyclooxygenase 2; MMP: matrix metallopeptidase; JNK: c-Jun N-terminal kinase.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="table-fn8-2041731415618342">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Flexercell model not specified.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section13-2041731415618342">
        <title>Impact on cytokine/growth factor production</title>
        <p>Growth factors and cytokines can have both autocrine and paracrine effects in the local microenvironment where they are produced. Therefore, the effect of stretch signals applied using Flexercell can give some indication regarding the potential influence of mechanical stretch signals in vivo and also potentially enable &#x201C;priming&#x201D; of cells to upregulate particular factors for therapeutic applications.</p>
        <p>Stretching PDL cells for 24&#x2009;h (5% elongation at 0.05&#x2009;Hz) enhanced TGF&#x3B2; production after 7&#x2009;days<sup><xref rid="bibr84-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></sup> but only in PDL cells from adult teeth and not deciduous teeth. This perhaps reflects the intrinsic difference in longevity between the two as TGF&#x3B2; has a prominent role in matrix formation, maturation, and scar tissue formation that is not needed by deciduous teeth that are shed. On the other hand, stretch signals led to a decrease in M-CSF levels, even after pre-stimulation with vitD3,<sup><xref rid="bibr84-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></sup> which normally stimulates M-CSF production. VEGF production by PDL cells was also upregulated after stretching,<sup><xref rid="bibr94-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,<xref rid="bibr95-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">95</xref></sup> as were osteogenic factors BMP2 and BMP6.<sup><xref rid="bibr94-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></sup> VEGF production by tendon fibroblasts was similarly increased and together with the simultaneous upregulation of PGE<sub>2</sub> expression was suggested as a mediator of inflammation and fibrosis, as typically responsible for carpal tunnel syndrome.<sup><xref rid="bibr113-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">113</xref></sup> This suggests that stretch-mediated upregulation of growth factors and cytokines is not necessarily a positive event for fibroblastic cells, and risk of scare tissue formation due to excessive stretch in vivo can perhaps be modeled in vitro using Flexercell systems.</p>
        <p>The magnitude of strain seems to be an important factor in determining cell responses. Low-magnitude tensile strain (from 2% to 8%) was found to have anti-inflammatory effects on PDL cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr78-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,<xref rid="bibr119-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,<xref rid="bibr120-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">120</xref></sup> For example, IL1-mediated transcription of IL1, IL6, and IL8 was blocked, whereas production of IL10, which in turn can block synthesis of IL1, IL6, and IL8,<sup><xref rid="bibr121-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">121</xref></sup> was enhanced.<sup><xref rid="bibr119-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">119</xref></sup> In this low range, strain was also found to significantly inhibit IL1-mediated activation of COX2 gene expression and PGE<sub>2</sub> synthesis in a dose-dependent fashion,<sup><xref rid="bibr78-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></sup> reinforcing the argument that low-magnitude strain is anti-inflammatory. In contrast, high strain levels (10%&#x2013;18.5% strain) induce pro-inflammatory responses such as nuclear factor-&#x3BA;B (NF-&#x3BA;B)-mediated COX2 gene expression.<sup><xref rid="bibr78-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></sup> Moreover, high strain levels (9% and 18%) significantly enhanced production of IL1 and PGE<sub>2</sub> and the effects were more prominent in PDL cells from aged tissue versus young.<sup><xref rid="bibr92-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></sup> Cellular aging was also found to impact significantly COX2 gene expression, with aged (late passage) PDL cells producing higher COX2 mRNA levels than young cells after strain.<sup><xref rid="bibr122-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">122</xref></sup></p>
        <p>High strain levels (18% elongation applied for 12&#x2009;h at 0.1&#x2009;Hz) were also found to significantly enhance NO production,<sup><xref rid="bibr123-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">123</xref></sup> which has many physiologic functions that include inflammation, which is likely in this case given the other reported inflammatory mediators upregulated by high-magnitude strain. In rabbit Achilles tendon fibroblasts, the application of strain in the presence of IL1 also led to a 17-fold increase in pro-MMP3 production, but no difference in COX2 expression was observed compared with IL1 treatment alone.<sup><xref rid="bibr124-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">124</xref></sup> Strain-induced expression of inflammatory genes could be suppressed by the addition of exogenous ATP to the culture.<sup><xref rid="bibr117-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">117</xref></sup></p>
        <p>Overall, it seems that a growth factor/cytokine expression profile associated with inflammation is produced in response to mechanical stretch signals that is magnitude dependent. However, low-magnitude stretch is actually anti-inflammatory, and this biphasic response runs parallel with physiologic scale observations where chronic overuse results in injury and inflammation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section14-2041731415618342">
        <title>Cellular maturation and differentiation</title>
        <p>Functional tendons are dependent on adequate cell&#x2013;cell communication and gap junctions are crucial for this.<sup><xref rid="bibr97-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">97</xref></sup> Specific gap junction proteins n-cadherin and vinculin are both significantly upregulated in tendon cells after exposure to cyclic stretch<sup><xref rid="bibr116-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">116</xref></sup> along with connexin-43, which is localized to gap junctions at the ends of actin filaments.<sup><xref rid="bibr118-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">118</xref></sup> Enhanced cell&#x2013;cell communication is very important for stretch-mediated responses, particularly so in 3D constructs populated with tendon fibroblasts, where application of mechanical strain using a non-Flexercell method resulted in a threefold increase in tensile strength of constructs compared with non-loaded constructs after 7&#x2009;days of loading.<sup><xref rid="bibr125-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">125</xref></sup> In addition, supplementing cultures with the anabolic steroid, nandrolone decanoate, synergistically enhances matrix remodeling and ultimately tensile strength of bioengineered tendons.<sup><xref rid="bibr126-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">126</xref></sup> Therefore, applying mechanical strain to tissue engineered constructs creates a more physiologically relevant tissue. Moreover, when considering information gained from many published Flexercell studies, translating the relevance of this information from 2D to 3D microenvironment needs to be considered.</p>
        <p>PDL cells can acquire a bone-like phenotype, and mechanical strain is generally considered to promote and enhance this. Wescott et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr94-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></sup> subjected PDL cells to 12% cyclic strain for up to 24&#x2009;h and then screened an array of 78 different genes associated with osteogenic differentiation and bone metabolism. Several genes associated with osteogenesis were upregulated, including BMP2, BMP6, ALP, SOX9, MSX1, and vascular endothelial growth factor A (VEGFA), suggesting that a program of osteogenic gene expression was invoked. However, there seems to be a minimum duration of exposure to strain, or culture period following exposure, that is required for osteogenic induction to take place as short-term exposure (6&#x2009;h) was insufficient to enhance the expression of any key osteogenic genes.<sup><xref rid="bibr93-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,<xref rid="bibr94-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></sup> Over a longer culture period of 48&#x2009;h, the expression levels of type I collagen and decorin were elevated after stretch of up to 18% elongation.<sup><xref rid="bibr90-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">90</xref></sup> Continuous cyclic strain of 9% or 18% elongation at 0.1&#x2009;Hz applied to PDL cells for up to 6&#x2009;days resulted in enhanced osteoblastic differentiation characterized by increased ALP activity and expression of OCN, with paralleled decrease in mitogenic potential and epidermal growth factor (EGF) receptor expression.<sup><xref rid="bibr88-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,<xref rid="bibr127-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">127</xref></sup> Differentiation was inhibited by the addition of EGF to the culture medium, which reversed the profile.</p>
        <p>In a separate study, ALP synthesis was downregulated in PDL cells subjected to cyclic stretch of 15% elongation at 0.5&#x2009;Hz and even treatment with vitamin D (an agonist of ALP production) was unable to compensate.<sup><xref rid="bibr80-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">80</xref></sup> Therefore, the PDL contains a source of multipotent cells that can differentiate toward a bone-forming phenotype, and a careful balance between both biological and mechanical signals is required to maintain the niche and direct cell fate. Furthermore, at high strain levels it seems that a fine balance between osteogenic differentiation and inflammation occurs. Similar to osteoblasts, in PDL cells, cyclic strain also suppresses osteoclastogenesis as although osteoclast genes OPG and RANKL are both upregulated,<sup><xref rid="bibr128-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">128</xref></sup> the former inhibits the stimulatory effects of the latter.</p>
        <p>In summary, mechanical stretch signals applied to tendon and ligament cells using Flexercell have been reported to be largely positive, with matrix synthesis and remodeling being upregulated when using moderate strain levels. Moderate strain levels also have documented anti-inflammatory properties and are able to abrogate the effects of cytokines on these cell types. Conversely, high strain levels induce inflammatory pathways and this likely reflects the potential tissue damage caused by high strains in vivo.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section15-2041731415618342">
      <title>Effect of mechanical strain on cartilage cells</title>
      <p>Hyaline cartilage has a crucial protective role in the bone&#x2013;bone contacts, such as knee, where it protects the ends of opposing bone structures and dissipates loads evenly across the full surface area of the cartilage. Consequently, in addition to the load bearing that is typically associated with cartilage function, the constituent chondrocytes also experience tensile and shear stresses.<sup><xref rid="bibr129-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">129</xref><xref rid="bibr130-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x2013;<xref rid="bibr131-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">131</xref></sup> A summary of studies assessing the impact of mechanical stretch on chondrocytes using Flexercell is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-2041731415618342">Table 5</xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="table5-2041731415618342" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summary of Flexercell studies and key findings using chondrocytes.</p>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2041731415618342-table5"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
              <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell type</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage of differentiation</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch device and regime</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key findings</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabbit articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 2%&#x2013;18%, 0.05&#x2009;Hz, in the presence or absence of IL1&#x3B2;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low stretch: inhibitor of IL1&#x3B2;-dependent NF-&#x3BA;B nuclear translocation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agarwal et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr132-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">132</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High stretch: involvement of NF-&#x3BA;B nuclear translocation and synthesis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell 2000, 7% elongation, 0.5&#x2009;Hz, cyclic stretch (1&#x2009;s on, 1&#x2009;s off)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upregulated expression of MMP13 and cathepsin B</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr133-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">133</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No effect on the expression of aggrecan and COL II</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 3%, 0.25&#x2009;Hz, in the presence or absence of IL1&#x3B2;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibitor of IL1&#x3B2;-dependent NF-&#x3BA;B nuclear translocation and cytoplasmic degradation of I&#x3BA;B&#x3B2; and I&#x3BA;B&#x3B1;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dossumbekova et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr134-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">134</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Human chondrosarcoma (HCS-2/8)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> high frequency: 30 cycles/min</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High magnitude and frequency gene expression of IL1 and MMP9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fujisawa et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr135-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">135</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mid frequency: 1 cycle/2&#x2009;min</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Continuous stress induces the production of IL1 and MMP9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low frequency: 1 cycle/4&#x2009;min</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bovine articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> higher stress at 10 cycles/min, 17%</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased proteoglycan synthesis at low frequency and magnitude</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fukuda et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr136-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">136</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower stress at 10 cycle/h, 5%</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreased proteoglycan synthesis at high frequency and magnitude</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabbit articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 0.05&#x2009;Hz, 20% elongation, in the presence or absence of IL1&#x3B2;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-inflammatory effect by inhibiting iNOS and therefore NO in IL1&#x3B2;-activated chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gassner et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr137-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">137</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabbit articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes (retain their differentiated phenotype)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 3 cycles/min consisting of 10&#x2009;s strain, 10&#x2009;s rest</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverses IL1&#x3B2;-induced suppression of proteoglycan synthesis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gassner et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr138-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">138</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bovine articular cartilage and human chondrosarcoma (105KC)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 24% maximal (average 10%), cyclic (2&#x2009;s on, 2&#x2009;s off), 1&#x2013;20&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary cells: increased COL II expression with no change in &#x3B2;1 integrin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holmvall et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr139-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">139</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105KC: increased &#x3B1;5 expression with no change in &#x3B2;1, &#x3B1;2 or &#x3B1;&#x3BD;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Porcine articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 10% strain, 0.5&#x2009;Hz, 1&#x2013;24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased NO, PGE<sub>2</sub> and COX2 expression</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huang et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr140-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">140</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anabolic response: Increased COL II and aggrecan expression as an early response</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catabolic response: Increased TGF&#x3B2; and MMP1 expression at 24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Human articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> &#x2212;20&#x2009;kPa, 0.5&#x2009;Hz, 24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased proliferation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lahiji et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr141-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">141</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enhanced expression of COL II and aggrecan</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enhanced integrin &#x3B1;2 but no change in &#x3B1;5 or &#x3B2;1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabbit articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes (retaining their differentiated phenotype)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 6%, 0.05&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abrogated TNF&#x3B1;-induced inhibition of proteoglycan synthesis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr87-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">87</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes (retaining their differentiated phenotype)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 3%, 0.25&#x2009;Hz, 4&#x2013;24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blocking of IL1&#x3B2;-dependent pro-inflammatory gene expression (iNOS, COX2, MMP9 and MMP13)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Madhavan et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr142-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">142</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bovine articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, 7%, the frequency (10 cycles/min, 3&#x2009;s)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enhanced NO synthesis that inhibited PG synthesis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matsukawa et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr143-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">143</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> elongation 7%, 30 cycles/min, 12&#x2013;24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protective effect of IL4 on matrix synthesis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shimizu et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr144-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">144</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 5, 17%</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreased proteoglycan synthesis and PKC activity</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tanaka et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr145-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">145</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bovine articular cartilage</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 3000, high (10 cycles/min), low (10 cycles/h)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caused depolymerization of HA and induced ROS generation</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yamazaki et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr146-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">146</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabbit fibrochondrocytes from TMJ</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes (retain their differentiated phenotype)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 6% stretch, 3 cycles/min, 0.05&#x2009;Hz</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretch suppresses IL1&#x3B2;-dependent induction of COX2 and PGE<sub>2</sub> synthesis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agarwal et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr147-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">147</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human chondrosarcoma (CS-OKB)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confluent</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-2041731415618342">a</xref></sup> 25%, 0.05&#x2009;Hz, 48&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Induces the expression of a heat shock protein termed stress-induced chondrocytic (SIC) 1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chano et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr148-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">148</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat fibrochondrocytes from TMJ</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes (retain their differentiated phenotype)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bioflex loading stations, 20%, 0.05&#x2009;Hz, 1&#x2013;20&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL1&#x3B2;-induced expression of several MMPs inhibited</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deschner et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr149-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">149</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat fibrochondrocytes from TMJ</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chondrocytes (retain their differentiated phenotype)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexercell 4000, 20%, 0.05&#x2009;Hz, 1&#x2013;24&#x2009;h</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibits IL1&#x3B2;-induced expression of TNF&#x3B1;, TNFR2 and iNOS, but not TNFR1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deschner et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr150-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">150</xref></sup></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="table-fn9-2041731415618342">
            <p>IL1&#x3B2;: interleukin 1&#x3B2;; NF-&#x3BA;B: nuclear factor-&#x3BA;B; MMP: matrix metallopeptidase; iNOS: inducible nitric oxide synthase; NO: nitric oxide; TNF&#x3B1;: tumor necrosis factor &#x3B1;; COX2: cyclooxygenase 2; PG: proteoglycan; PKC: protein kinase C; ROS: reactive oxygen species; TMJ: temporomandibular joint; PGE<sub>2</sub>: prostaglandin E2; TNFR: tumor necrosis factor receptor; I&#x3BA;B: nuclear factor of kappa light polypeptide gene enhancer in B-cells inhibitor; HA: Hyaluronan.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="table-fn10-2041731415618342">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>Flexercell model not specified.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <sec id="section16-2041731415618342">
        <title>Impact on cell survival, proliferation, and growth</title>
        <p>Chondrocyte proliferation is upregulated in response to strain.<sup><xref rid="bibr151-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">151</xref></sup> It is not just magnitude of strain that can impact cell responses, but also frequency. This was demonstrated when mechanical stretch of 3% elongation was applied to chondrocytes at 2, 30, or 150 cycles/min (corresponding to 0.03, 0.5, or 2.5&#x2009;Hz), with the higher frequency increasing DNA synthesis.<sup><xref rid="bibr152-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">152</xref></sup> From this observation we can conclude that a delicate interplay between several factors including magnitude and frequency of applied stretch can influence cell behavior.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section17-2041731415618342">
        <title>Matrix production</title>
        <p>Multiple studies using hyaline cartilage have concluded that application of mechanical stretch increases production of the major collagen component of cartilage, type II collagen,<sup><xref rid="bibr139-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,<xref rid="bibr140-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,<xref rid="bibr152-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>,<xref rid="bibr153-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">153</xref></sup> and the integrin subunit &#x3B1;2,<sup><xref rid="bibr139-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,<xref rid="bibr153-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">153</xref></sup> which binds to collagen. Similarly, the proteoglycan aggrecan is also upregulated<sup><xref rid="bibr140-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,<xref rid="bibr143-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>,<xref rid="bibr152-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>,<xref rid="bibr153-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">153</xref></sup> as are several important cartilage glycosaminoglycans (GAGs) including chondroitin-6-sulfate, hyaluronic acid, and dermatan sulfate.<sup><xref rid="bibr154-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">154</xref></sup></p>
        <p>However, not all studies agree as stretch was found to downregulate transcript levels of aggrecan and type II collagen, but this could be reversed by the addition of IL4.<sup><xref rid="bibr144-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">144</xref></sup> Hyaluronic acid was also found to undergo depolymerization in the presence of strain due to generation of reactive oxygen species.<sup><xref rid="bibr146-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">146</xref></sup> These conflicting observations can perhaps be explained by the recurring theme of magnitude-dependent effects. In the case of matrix production, particularly proteoglycans that along with their component GAGs are important for producing a highly hydrated matrix, the effects of stretch are magnitude dependent. Low-magnitude strain enhances proteoglycan production and matrix synthesis, whereas high-magnitude strain diminishes it resulting in ECM degradation and onset of inflammation.<sup><xref rid="bibr132-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>,<xref rid="bibr133-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,<xref rid="bibr135-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>,<xref rid="bibr136-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,<xref rid="bibr155-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">155</xref></sup> The process is dependent on protein kinase C activity.<sup><xref rid="bibr136-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">136</xref></sup> Moreover, application of high-magnitude cyclic strain to cultured chondrocytes was found to upregulate the expression of MMPs that degrade cartilage ECM.<sup><xref rid="bibr133-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,<xref rid="bibr135-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>,<xref rid="bibr155-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">155</xref></sup> Cyclic strain is able to prevent suppression of proteoglycan synthesis caused by IL1<sup><xref rid="bibr138-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,<xref rid="bibr142-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">142</xref></sup> and tumor necrosis factor &#x3B1; (TNF&#x3B1;)<sup><xref rid="bibr87-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">87</xref></sup> but again may be magnitude dependent.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section18-2041731415618342">
        <title>Impact on cytokine/growth factor production</title>
        <p>In terms of inflammation, the same biphasic response as seen for tendon/ligament cells can be observed. Exposure of chondrocytes to low magnitudes of strain (&lt;8% elongation) is reported to invoke anti-inflammatory effects, whereas high strain levels (up to 18% elongation) augment the inflammatory response.<sup><xref rid="bibr132-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">132</xref></sup> This indicates some conservation in responses to different cell populations from throughout the musculoskeletal system with respect to mechanical signal responsiveness. In particular, low-level strain has generally been observed to block the expression of inflammation-related genes that augment cartilage destruction.<sup><xref rid="bibr87-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>,<xref rid="bibr132-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>,<xref rid="bibr134-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>,<xref rid="bibr137-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>,<xref rid="bibr142-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>,<xref rid="bibr147-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,<xref rid="bibr149-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>,<xref rid="bibr150-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">150</xref></sup> For example, using high frequency and low strain (3% elongation at 25&#x2009;MHz), IL1 pro-inflammatory activity was inhibited, due to block of IL1-mediated NF-&#x3BA;B nuclear translocation,<sup><xref rid="bibr134-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">134</xref></sup> in a transforming growth factor-&#x3B2;-activated kinase-1 (TAK1)-dependent fashion.<sup><xref rid="bibr156-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">156</xref></sup> This prevented subsequent transcription of inflammatory gene targets, which normally result from NF-&#x3BA;B activation. Similarly, TNF&#x3B1;-mediated inflammatory responses were blocked by strain in vitro.<sup><xref rid="bibr87-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">87</xref></sup></p>
        <p>There are some anomalies to this general trend however, with high-magnitude strain (20% elongation) applied at low frequency (0.05&#x2009;Hz) reported to produce anti-inflammatory effects by downregulating IL1-dependent inducible NOS production.<sup><xref rid="bibr137-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">137</xref></sup> Additionally, cyclic strain of 7% elongation at 0.5&#x2009;Hz was found to induce IL1&#x3B2; expression and that of MMP13 and cathepsin B,<sup><xref rid="bibr133-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">133</xref></sup> both proteolytic enzymes associated with cartilage pathogenesis.</p>
        <p>Interestingly, one study reported that in the presence of a single strain regime of 10% elongation at 0.5&#x2009;Hz, both catabolic/pro-inflammatory and anabolic responses were observed.<sup><xref rid="bibr140-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">140</xref></sup> While production of NO, PGE<sub>2</sub>, and COX2 (characteristic of a pro-inflammatory response) were increased, so too were expression levels of type II collagen and the cartilage-specific proteoglycan aggrecan, as mentioned above. This early response was then replaced by elevations of expression of TGF&#x3B2;1 and TGF&#x3B2;3, along with MMP1, indicating that matrix remodeling ensues. Collectively, the above data echoes at the cellular level the patient response where gentle exercise and joint mobility are reported to be beneficial for inflamed joints.<sup><xref rid="bibr157-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,<xref rid="bibr158-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">158</xref></sup></p>
        <p>In summary, Flexercell studies indicate that low to moderate levels of strain generally promote cartilage anabolic responses, terms of chondrocyte proliferation, GAG, and proteoglycan production, while also conferring anti-inflammatory effects. However, high levels of strain have a tendency to drive inflammatory responses and provide a good deal of correlation to the trauma and injury associated with high strain and overuse in patients.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section19-2041731415618342">
      <title>The effect of strain applied using Flexercell on mechanotransduction mediators</title>
      <p>Most of the bone-stimulating effects of mechanical strain occur due to the activation of mechanotransduction pathways, and the major cell surface receptors involved in these pathways are the integrins. In human osteosarcoma cells, a strain regime of 20&#x2009;kPa at 0.05&#x2009;Hz resulted in the upregulation of &#x3B2;1 integrin mRNA expression<sup><xref rid="bibr11-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> along with redistribution of &#x3B2;1 integrin subunits from the cytoplasm to the cell membrane.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> However, &#x3B1;v integrin expression and distribution were unaffected by mechanical strain,<sup><xref rid="bibr11-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> indicating that functional activation and continued recruitment of integrins in response to strain are specific to certain subunits of integrin. Interestingly, vitronectin and OPN, both ligands for &#x3B1;v-containing &#x3B1;v&#x3B2;3, induce greater calcium influx into osteoblasts than other matrix molecules,<sup><xref rid="bibr159-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">159</xref></sup> and the lack of change in &#x3B1;v integrin subunit expression and distribution upon mechanical loading using Flexercell suggests that the cell response to this form of mechanical strain is not calcium-dependent. It has also been reported that both &#x3B1;2&#x3B2;1 and &#x3B1;5&#x3B2;1 can transmit the effect of stretching from the extracellular environment to activate ERK downstream.<sup><xref rid="bibr24-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> However, it seems that the &#x3B1;-subunits are the most potent mediators, not &#x3B2;1, and their signal transduction capacity is actin dependent.<sup><xref rid="bibr24-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="bibr160-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">160</xref></sup> Disruption of the actin cytoskeleton, for example, by treatment with cytochalasin D, an actin-depolymerizing agent, attenuates stress response pathways in osteoblast cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr161-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">161</xref><xref rid="bibr162-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x2013;<xref rid="bibr163-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">163</xref></sup> This indicates the importance of the cytoskeleton in sustaining mechanotransduction from extracellular input signals.</p>
      <p>Mechanotransduction downstream of integrins involves the coordinated regulation of several other key molecules. Src kinase interacts with integrin intracellular domains<sup><xref rid="bibr24-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> and FAK<sup><xref rid="bibr10-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> at the focal adhesion site when mechanical strain is applied. In osteoblasts, this universally leads to stretch-induced activation of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathways and in particular ERK, a key MAPK effector molecule that activates mechanoresponsive transcription factors.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bibr10-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bibr13-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bibr15-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bibr18-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bibr24-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="bibr26-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="bibr164-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">164</xref></sup> At the focal adhesion site formed upon mechanical activation of integrins, FAK also undergoes enhanced and sustained association with another tyrosine kinase, proline-rich tyrosine kinase 2 (PYK2),<sup><xref rid="bibr10-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bibr16-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> which seems to stablize FAK and remove the inhibitory Hic5 adaptor protein from the focal adhesion complex upon activation.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Collectively, these data confirm that integrins and their associated intracellular partners are necessary for signal transduction downstream of the strain stimulus to be executed.</p>
      <p>Canonical wnt signaling in Flexercell-stretched osteoblasts is highly activated, with enhanced &#x3B2;-catenin transcriptional activity reported.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="bibr25-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> This leads to upregulation of numerous wnt target genes such as those encoding cell cycle proteins, the gap junction protein connexin-43, and other transcription factors.<sup><xref rid="bibr25-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Phosphorylation of AKT can also promote &#x3B2;-catenin transcriptional activity via glycogen synthase kinase 3 (GSK&#x3B2;) inactivation and subsequent translocation of &#x3B2;-catenin to the nucleus, where the wnt target genes Wisp1 and Cox2 are then transcribed.<sup><xref rid="bibr165-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">165</xref></sup> Upregulation of the wnt target gene encoding connexin-43 seems to have a role in enhancing cell&#x2013;cell communication among mechanically stimulated osteoblasts by enhancing gap junction communication due to increased levels of phosphorylated connexin-43 protein,<sup><xref rid="bibr166-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>,<xref rid="bibr167-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">167</xref></sup> and in tendon cells its colocalization with actin presumably facilitates cell communication in the direction of force application.</p>
      <p>The role of integrins in mechanotransduction is explicit as they anchor cells to the ECM substrate in which they reside.<sup><xref rid="bibr168-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>,<xref rid="bibr169-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">169</xref></sup> Less obvious candidates for mechanotransduction are cell surface receptors that do not have an active role in physical anchorage of cells to ECM. It is well known that androgens, in combination with mechanical cues, can control bone metabolism and invoke a shift from high turnover to osteoanabolic mode. Typically, mechanical signaling via the estrogen receptors (ERs) enhances osteoblast proliferation.<sup><xref rid="bibr170-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">170</xref></sup> ERs have a critical role in mechanotransduction and ERK activation, as osteoblasts from ER&#x3B1;&#x3B2;<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup> mice lacking both &#x3B1; and &#x3B2; forms of ER were unable to activate ERK when stimulated with 5% elongation at 0.05&#x2009;Hz.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> This phenotype could be partially rescued by transfecting ER&#x3B1;&#x3B2;<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup> osteoblasts with cDNA for either receptor or fully rescued by transfection with cDNA for both receptors. Additionally, the active estrogen compound estradiol acts in synergy with mechanical strain to promote ER-dependent ALP activity.<sup><xref rid="bibr171-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">171</xref></sup> U2OS osteosarcoma cells that do not express ERs and have intrinsically low ALP activity were compared with transfected U2OS cells expressing either ER&#x3B1; or ER&#x3B2; for COL1 expression and ALP activity after being subjected to 1.5% cyclic strain at 0.05&#x2009;Hz. Mechanical strain increased ALP activity and decreased COL1 expression in ER&#x3B1; and ER&#x3B2; mutants, with estrogen having a synergistic effect on ALP activity. However, estrogen itself is dispensable to the process of ER-mediated mechanotransduction as transfecting ER&#x3B1;&#x3B2;<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup> osteoblasts with mutant ERs incapable of binding to estrogen did not impair ERK activation, demonstrating that the process was not dependent on estrogen. Even so, it cannot be discounted that differences in the cell lines or the strain regimes applied to cells may have a bearing on the outcome.</p>
      <p>Integrins that mediate cell adhesion initiate mechanotransduction signals and have shown significant impact on ligament cells upon stretch stimulation. In PDL fibroblasts, assessment of integrin gene expression showed that both &#x3B1;6 and &#x3B2;1 were upregulated by stretch.<sup><xref rid="bibr79-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></sup> Cells from the ACL or MCL plated onto type I collagen, fibronectin, or laminin express elevated levels of both &#x3B1;5 and &#x3B2;1 when stretched at 5% elongation for 2&#x2009;h,<sup><xref rid="bibr81-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></sup> and in avian tendon cells, src kinase phosphorylation is also increased after mechanical stimulation.<sup><xref rid="bibr96-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">96</xref></sup> In 3D collagen gels loaded with ACL fibroblasts, strain enhances both &#x3B1;5 and &#x3B2;1, but not in &#x3B1;1 expression.<sup><xref rid="bibr82-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">82</xref></sup> However, the expression of the &#x3B1;5 integrin subunit in PDL cell monolayers subjected to stretch was actually found to be downregulated upon application of 20&#x2009;kPa negative pressure to each well for 12&#x2009;h.<sup><xref rid="bibr79-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></sup></p>
      <p>As well as integrin-mediated mechanotransduction, calcium signaling has an important role in cell responsiveness to mechanical forces. Calcium signaling between MCL cells is enhanced by mechanical stretch, as determined by their ability to maintain a calcium wave between cells both aligned longitudinally in microgrooves and in non-aligned cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr86-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">86</xref></sup> In the case of tendon cells, activation of JNK, a &#x201C;stress-activated protein kinase,&#x201D; occurs in response to mechanical strain, and the level of JNK activation is dependent on magnitude of strain applied.<sup><xref rid="bibr111-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">111</xref></sup> It also seems to take place downstream of calcium signaling as increased intracellular calcium levels also enhance JNK activation independent of strain.<sup><xref rid="bibr111-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">111</xref></sup> Chronic, sustained activation of JNK in tendon cells could result in cell death and tendon injury.</p>
      <p>There was also prominent upregulation of ulnar collateral ligament (UNCL) protein in PDL cells after applied strain.<sup><xref rid="bibr83-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">83</xref></sup> UNCL has a central role in mechanotransduction pathways based on evidence that loss-of-function mutations to the homolog in <italic>Drosophila</italic> result in failure of mechanotransduction<sup><xref rid="bibr172-2041731415618342" ref-type="bibr">172</xref></sup> and so might have important function in ligament physiology.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section20-2041731415618342">
      <title>Summary</title>
      <p>Cell behavior is regulated by both biochemical and physical signals. The importance of biophysical cues in determining cell phenotype is becoming more widely understood, as are mechanotransduction pathways that are activated upon mechanical stimulation. Application of mechanical strain, most commonly applied using the Flexercell system, can provide physical stimulation to cells in the bone and surrounding tissues and aid our understanding of mechanical strain impact on health and injury. It may also potentially be used as a means of priming cell components of the tissues prior to seeding them into scaffolds for tissue engineering and in vivo transplantation.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This work was supported by the Priority Research Centers Program (Grant No. 2009-0093829), the Global Research Laboratory Program (Grant No. 2015032163) and KRIBB Research Initiative Program, Republic of Korea.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bibr1-2041731415618342">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brindley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moorthy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Bioprocess forces and their impact on cell behavior: implications for bone regeneration therapy</article-title>. <source>J Tissue Eng</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>2011</volume>: <fpage>620247</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21904661</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr2-2041731415618342">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeatts</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Bone tissue engineering bioreactors: dynamic culture and the influence of shear stress</article-title>. <source>Bone</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>181</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20932947</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr3-2041731415618342">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banes</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A new vacuum-operated stress-providing instrument that applies static or variable duration cyclic tension or compression to cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source>
<year>1985</year>; <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3900107</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr4-2041731415618342">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein-Nulend</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanotransduction in bone&#x2013;role of the lacuno-canalicular network</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>13</volume>(<issue>Suppl.</issue>): <fpage>S101</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>S112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10352151</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr5-2041731415618342">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liegibel</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomakidi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Concerted action of androgens and mechanical strain shifts bone metabolism from high turnover into an osteoanabolic mode</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>196</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1387</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1392</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12438430</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr6-2041731415618342">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of different magnitudes of mechanical strain on Osteoblasts in vitro</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>344</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>122</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16603128</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr7-2041731415618342">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Different magnitudes of tensile strain induce human osteoblasts differentiation associated with the activation of ERK1/2 phosphorylation</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>2322</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2332</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19330078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr8-2041731415618342">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotkin</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gortazar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A novel ligand-independent function of the estrogen receptor is essential for osteocyte and osteoblast mechanotransduction</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>282</volume>(<issue>35</issue>): <fpage>25501</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25508</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17609204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr9-2041731415618342">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Uniaxial mechanical strain: an in vitro correlate to distraction osteogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Surg Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>143</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>329</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>336</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17950332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr10-2041731415618342">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boutahar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guignandon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vico</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical strain on osteoblasts activates autophosphorylation of focal adhesion kinase (FAK) and proline-rich tyrosine kinase 2 (PYK2) tyrosine sites involved in ERK activation</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>30588</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>30599</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15096502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr11-2041731415618342">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bumann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A molecular mechanism of integrin regulation from bone cells stimulated by orthodontic forces</article-title>. <source>Eur J Orthod</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>227</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>235</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8791887</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr12-2041731415618342">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cillo</surname><given-names>JE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Gassner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Koepsel</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Growth factor and cytokine gene expression in mechanically strained human osteoblast-like cells: implications for distraction osteogenesis</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>90</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>147</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>154</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10936833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr13-2041731415618342">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahnert</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Response to mechanical strain in an immortalized pre-osteoblast cell is dependent on ERK1/2</article-title>. <source>J Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>207</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>454</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>460</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16419041</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr14-2041731415618342">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Linossier</surname><given-names>M-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Malaval</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical signals modulated vascular endothelial growth factor-A (VEGF-A) alternative splicing in osteoblastic cells through actin polymerisation</article-title>. <source>Bone</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>42</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1092</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18374641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr15-2041731415618342">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Granet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutahar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vico</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>MAPK and SRC-kinases control EGR-1 and NF-&#x3BA;B inductions by changes in mechanical environment in osteoblasts</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>284</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>622</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>631</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11396946</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr16-2041731415618342">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guignandon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutahar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic strain promotes shuttling of PYK2/Hic-5 complex from focal contacts in osteoblast-like cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>343</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>407</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>414</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16546139</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr17-2041731415618342">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>TOPGAL mice show that the canonical Wnt signaling pathway is active during bone development and growth and is activated by mechanical loading in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1103</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1113</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15940363</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr18-2041731415618342">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weyts</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Westbroek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Stretch-induced phosphorylation of ERK1/2 depends on differentiation stage of osteoblasts</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biochem</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>93</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>542</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>551</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15378606</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr19-2041731415618342">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Karmin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical loading differentially regulates membrane-bound and soluble RANKL availability in MC3T3-E1 cells</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>1068</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>568</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>572</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16831954</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr20-2041731415618342">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Centrella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Strain-dependent control of transforming growth factor-&#x3B2; function in osteoblasts in an in vitro model: biochemical events associated with distraction osteogenesis</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>116</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>224</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>233</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15988272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr21-2041731415618342">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Z-P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Strain-related collagen gene expression in human osteoblast-like cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Tissue Res</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>322</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>331</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>334</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16133149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr22-2041731415618342">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motokawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaku</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of cyclic tensile forces on the expression of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and macrophage-colony-stimulating factor (M-CSF) in murine osteoblastic MC3T3-E1 cells</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>84</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>422</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>427</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15840777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr23-2041731415618342">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narutomi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic mechanical strain induces interleukin-6 expression via prostaglandin E2 production by cyclooxygenase-2 in MC3T3-E1 osteoblast-like cells</article-title>. <source>J Oral Biosci</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>65</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr24-2041731415618342">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plotkin</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stimulation prevents osteocyte apoptosis: requirement of integrins, Src kinases, and ERKs</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>289</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>C633</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>C643</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15872009</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr25-2041731415618342">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterjee-Kishore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaworsky</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Wnt/&#x3B2;-catenin signaling is a normal physiological response to mechanical loading in bone</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>281</volume>(<issue>42</issue>): <fpage>31720</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>31728</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16908522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr26-2041731415618342">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toyoshita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koshino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>CYP24 promoter activity is affected by mechanical stress and mitogen-activated protein kinase in MG63 osteoblast-like cells</article-title>. <source>&#x65E5;&#x672C;&#x88DC;&#x7DB4;&#x6B6F;&#x79D1;&#x5B66;&#x4F1A;&#x96D1;&#x8A8C;</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">Nihon Hotetsu Shika Gakkai Zasshi</trans-source>] <year>2008</year>; <volume>52</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18467787</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr27-2041731415618342">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visconti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of strain on bone nodule formation by rat osteogenic cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>Arch Oral Biol</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>485</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>492</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15099806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr28-2041731415618342">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The effects of mechanical stimulation on the distribution of beta 1 integrin and expression of beta 1-integrin mRNA in TE-85 human osteosarcoma cells</article-title>. <source>Arch Oral Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>257</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>264</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7541624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr29-2041731415618342">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mikuni-Takagaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Distinct responses of different populations of bone cells to mechanical stress</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>137</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>2028</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2035</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8612544</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr30-2041731415618342">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Centrella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Control of TGF-beta receptor expression in bone</article-title>. <source>Front Biosci</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>d113</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>d124</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9422710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr31-2041731415618342">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cloning the promoter for transforming growth factor-beta type III receptor. Basal and conditional expression in fetal rat osteoblasts</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>274</volume>(<issue>43</issue>): <fpage>30487</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>30494</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10521429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr32-2041731415618342">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Centrella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casinghino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Independent changes in type I and type II receptors for transforming growth factor beta induced by bone morphogenetic protein 2 parallel expression of the osteoblast phenotype</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>3273</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3281</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7760823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr33-2041731415618342">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baylink</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkelman</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Growth factors to stimulate bone formation</article-title>. <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>
<year>1993</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 2</issue>): <fpage>S565</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>S572</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8122528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr34-2041731415618342">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neidlinger-Wilke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stalla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Claes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Human osteoblasts from younger normal and osteoporotic donors show differences in proliferation and TGF beta-release in response to cyclic strain</article-title>. <source>J Biomech</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>28</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1411</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8666581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr35-2041731415618342">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikuni-Takagaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanotransduction in stretched osteocytes&#x2013;temporal expression of immediate early and other genes</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>246</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>404</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9610372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr36-2041731415618342">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lean</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Osteocytic expression of mRNA for c-fos and IGF-I: an immediate early gene response to an osteogenic stimulus</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>270</volume>(<issue>6 Pt 1</issue>): <fpage>E937</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>E945</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8764176</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr37-2041731415618342">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skerry</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitensky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chayen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Early strain-related changes in enzyme activity in osteocytes following bone loading in vivo</article-title>. <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>
<year>1989</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>783</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>788</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2816520</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr38-2041731415618342">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddhivarn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Banes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical loading and delta12prostaglandin J2 induce bone morphogenetic protein-2, peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma-1, and bone nodule formation in an osteoblastic cell line</article-title>. <source>J Periodontal Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>42</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>383</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>392</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17760815</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr39-2041731415618342">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwan Tat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Padrines</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Theoleyre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>IL-6, RANKL, TNF-alpha/IL-1: interrelations in bone resorption pathophysiology</article-title>. <source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>49</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14746813</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr40-2041731415618342">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Deyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stress directly suppresses osteoclast differentiation in RAW264.7 cells</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Med</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>291</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18288375</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr41-2041731415618342">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddhivarn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Banes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prostaglandin D2 pathway and peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma-1 expression are induced by mechanical loading in an osteoblastic cell line</article-title>. <source>J Periodontal Res</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>92</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16499711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr42-2041731415618342">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofbauer</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Heufelder</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Role of receptor activator of nuclear factor-kappaB ligand and osteoprotegerin in bone cell biology</article-title>. <source>J Mol Med</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>79</volume>(<issue>5&#x2013;6</issue>): <fpage>243</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11485016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr43-2041731415618342">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatsumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stretch induces activation of skeletal muscle satellite cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>Exp Cell Res</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>267</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>107</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11412043</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr44-2041731415618342">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatsumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Release of hepatocyte growth factor from mechanically stretched skeletal muscle satellite cells and role of pH and nitric oxide</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>2909</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2918</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12181355</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr45-2041731415618342">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatsumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stretch-induced activation of skeletal muscle satellite cells is dependent on nitric oxide production <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>73</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>235</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr46-2041731415618342">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Knobloch</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Anghelina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Biomechanical signals upregulate myogenic gene induction in the presence or absence of inflammation</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>293</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>C267</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>C276</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17392379</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr47-2041731415618342">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwanuma</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of mechanical stretching on caspase and IGF-1 expression during the proliferation process of myoblasts</article-title>. <source>Zoolog Sci</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>242</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>247</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18393560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr48-2041731415618342">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Dynamic transcription programs during ES cell differentiation towards mesoderm in serum versus serum-freeBMP4 culture</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>365</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17925037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr49-2041731415618342">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>REDD2 is enriched in skeletal muscle and inhibits mTOR signaling in response to leucine and stretch</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>296</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>C583</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>C592</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19129461</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr50-2041731415618342">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatsumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuhashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative analysis of mechanical stretch-induced activation activity of back and leg muscle satellite cells <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>75</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>345</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>351</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr51-2041731415618342">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankoda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Matrix metalloproteinase-2 mediates stretch-induced activation of skeletal muscle satellite cells in a nitric oxide-dependent manner</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>2183</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2191</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18403250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr52-2041731415618342">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boonen</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Langelaan</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Polak</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of a combined mechanical stimulation protocol: value for skeletal muscle tissue engineering</article-title>. <source>J Biomech</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>43</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1514</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1521</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20189177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr53-2041731415618342">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic mechanical strain inhibits skeletal myogenesis through activation of focal adhesion kinase, Rac-1 GTPase, and NF-&#x3BA;B transcription factor</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>13</issue>): <fpage>1524</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1535</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466361</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr54-2041731415618342">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurokawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of stretching stimulation with different rates on the expression of MyHC mRNA in mouse cultured myoblasts</article-title>. <source>Biomed Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>28</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>25</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17379954</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr55-2041731415618342">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Caspase-3-mediated cyclic stretch-induced myoblast apoptosis via a Fas/FasL-independent signaling pathway during myogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biochem</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>107</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>834</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>844</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19415683</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr56-2041731415618342">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The dynamics of the nitric oxide release-transient from stretched muscle cells</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>625</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>631</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18694846</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr57-2041731415618342">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic stretch translocates the &#x3B1;2-subunit of the Na pump to plasma membrane in skeletal muscle cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>348</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>750</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>757</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16893515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr58-2041731415618342">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Truskey</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of cyclic stretch on &#x3B2;1D-integrin expression and activation of FAK and RhoA</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>292</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>C2057</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>C2069</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17267546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr59-2041731415618342">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atherton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Szewczyk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Selby</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic stretch reduces myofibrillar protein synthesis despite increases in FAK and anabolic signalling in L6 cells</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>587</volume>(<issue>14</issue>): <fpage>3719</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3727</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19470773</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr60-2041731415618342">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Feeback</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical load induces sarcoplasmic wounding and FGF release in differentiated human skeletal muscle cultures</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>502</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>509</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8647349</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr61-2041731415618342">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demoule</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Decailliot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Relationship between pressure-volume curve and markers for collagen turn-over in early acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Med</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>413</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>420</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16479381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr62-2041731415618342">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebihara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Danialou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical ventilation protects against diaphragm injury in sepsis: interaction of oxidative and mechanical stresses</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>165</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>221</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>228</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11790659</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr63-2041731415618342">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuyama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of heat stress and mechanical stretch on protein expression in cultured skeletal muscle cells</article-title>. <source>Pflugers Arch</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>447</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>247</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14534791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr64-2041731415618342">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hornberger</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Intracellular signaling specificity in response to uniaxial vs. multiaxial stretch: implications for mechanotransduction</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>288</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>C185</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>C194</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15371259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr65-2041731415618342">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hornberger</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Regulation of skeletal muscle mass through stretch-induced signaling events</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Illinois at Chicago</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr66-2041731415618342">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubatsch</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jasmin</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stimulation increases expression of acetylcholinesterase in cultured myotubes</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>273</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>C2002</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>C2009</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr67-2041731415618342">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitsumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Klip</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Development regulation of the subcellular distribution and glycosylation of GLUT1 and GLUT4 glucose transporters during myogenesis of L6 muscle cells</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1992</year>; <volume>267</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>4957</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4962</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1311324</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr68-2041731415618342">
        <label>68</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name><surname>Lusis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tidball</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Null mutation of myeloperoxidase in mice prevents mechanical activation of neutrophil lysis of muscle cell membranes in vitro and in vivo</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>565</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15790660</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr69-2041731415618342">
        <label>69</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pizza</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cytokines derived from cultured skeletal muscle cells after mechanical strain promote neutrophil chemotaxis in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>106</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>130</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>137</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18974369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr70-2041731415618342">
        <label>70</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sampaolesi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Stretch-induced cell damage in sarcoglycan-deficient myotubes</article-title>. <source>Pflugers Arch</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>442</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>161</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11417209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr71-2041731415618342">
        <label>71</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsivitse</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mylona</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical loading and injury induce human myotubes to release neutrophil chemoattractants</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>288</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>C721</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>C729</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15548571</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr72-2041731415618342">
        <label>72</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hornberger</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuppard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stimuli regulate rapamycin-sensitive signalling by a phosphoinositide 3-kinase-, protein kinase B- and growth factor-independent mechanism</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>380</volume>(<issue>Pt 3</issue>): <fpage>795</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>804</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15030312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr73-2041731415618342">
        <label>73</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilipowicz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Yablonka-Reuveni</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>C-Met expression and mechanical activation of satellite cells on cultured muscle fibers</article-title>. <source>J Histochem Cytochem</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>51</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>1437</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1445</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14566016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr74-2041731415618342">
        <label>74</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Nitric oxide-dependence of satellite stem cell activation and quiescence on normal skeletal muscle fibers</article-title>. <source>Dev Dyn</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>236</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>240</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>250</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17117435</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr75-2041731415618342">
        <label>75</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurokawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative metagenomics revealed commonly enriched gene sets in human gut microbiomes</article-title>. <source>DNA Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>181</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17916580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr76-2041731415618342">
        <label>76</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Galeotti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<source>Neisseria meningitidis antigens and compositions</source>. Patent, <year>2009</year>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.google.co.in/patents/EP2261345A3?cl=ko">http://www.google.co.in/patents/EP2261345A3?cl=ko</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr77-2041731415618342">
        <label>77</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartmell</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Uniaxial cyclic strain of human adipose-derived mesenchymal stem cells and C2C12 myoblasts in coculture</article-title>. <source>J Tissue Eng</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>5</volume>: 2041731414530138.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr78-2041731415618342">
        <label>78</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Seyedain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A central role for the nuclear factor-&#x3BA;B pathway in anti-inflammatory and proinflammatory actions of mechanical strain</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>899</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>901</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12670873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr79-2041731415618342">
        <label>79</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolcato-Bellemin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkaim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Abehsera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Expression of mRNAs encoding for &#x3B1; and &#x3B2; integrin subunits, MMPs, and TIMPs in stretched human periodontal ligament and gingival fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>79</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1712</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1716</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11023268</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr80-2041731415618342">
        <label>80</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cytoskeletal changes and the system of regulation of alkaline phosphatase activity in human periodontal ligament cells induced by mechanical stress</article-title>. <source>Cell Biochem Funct</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>256</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15248185</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr81-2041731415618342">
        <label>81</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hannafin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Attia</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Henshaw</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of cyclic strain and plating matrix on cell proliferation and integrin expression by ligament fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>149</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16435352</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr82-2041731415618342">
        <label>82</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henshaw</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Attia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhargava</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Canine ACL fibroblast integrin expression and cell alignment in response to cyclic tensile strain in three-dimensional collagen gels</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>481</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>490</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16453340</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr83-2041731415618342">
        <label>83</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Expression of UNCL during development of periodontal tissue and response of periodontal ligament fibroblasts to mechanical stress in vivo and in vitro</article-title>. <source>Cell Tissue Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>327</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>25</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17004066</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr84-2041731415618342">
        <label>84</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuzawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cytokine secretion of periodontal ligament fibroblasts derived from human deciduous teeth: effect of mechanical stress on the secretion of transforming growth factor-&#x3B2; 1 and macrophage colony stimulating factor</article-title>. <source>J Periodontal Res</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>34</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>235</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>243</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10567946</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr85-2041731415618342">
        <label>85</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CMH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Time-dependent increases in type-III collagen gene expression in medical collateral ligament fibroblasts under cyclic strains</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>220</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>227</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10815822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr86-2041731415618342">
        <label>86</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Ligament cells stretch-adapted on a microgrooved substrate increase intercellular communication in response to a mechanical stimulus</article-title>. <source>J Biomech</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>38</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1653</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1664</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15958223</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr87-2041731415618342">
        <label>87</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gassner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Tumor necrosis factor &#x3B1;-dependent proinflammatory gene induction is inhibited by cyclic tensile strain in articular chondrocytes in vitro</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>44</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>2311</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2319</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11665971</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr88-2041731415618342">
        <label>88</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Role of epidermal growth factor and its receptor in mechanical stress-induced differentiation of human periodontal ligament cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>Arch Oral Biol</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>43</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>987</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>997</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9877330</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr89-2041731415618342">
        <label>89</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Marui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitora</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stretching force promotes collagen synthesis by cultured cells from human ligamentum flavum via transforming growth factor-&#x3B2;1</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1380</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1386</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12472256</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr90-2041731415618342">
        <label>90</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Podyma-Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Modulation of extracellular matrix synthesis and alkaline phosphatase activity of periodontal ligament cells by mechanical stress</article-title>. <source>J Periodontal Res</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>110</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>117</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15733145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr91-2041731415618342">
        <label>91</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Abiko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Low-energy diode laser irradiation reduced plasminogen activator activity in human periodontal ligament cells</article-title>. <source>Lasers Surg Med</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>456</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>463</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9365956</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr92-2041731415618342">
        <label>92</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Uesu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Stimulation of prostaglandin E2 and Interleukin-1&#x3B2; production from old rat periodontal ligament cells subjected to mechanical stress</article-title>. <source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>55</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>B489</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>B495</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr93-2041731415618342">
        <label>93</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The induction of c-fos mRNA expression by mechanical stress in human periodontal ligament cells</article-title>. <source>Arch Oral Biol</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>47</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>465</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>471</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12102763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr94-2041731415618342">
        <label>94</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wescott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinkerton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaffey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Osteogenic gene expression by human periodontal ligament cells under cyclic tension</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>86</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1212</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1216</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18037658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr95-2041731415618342">
        <label>95</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Murota</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stress induces production of angiogenic regulators in cultured human gingival and periodontal ligament fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>J Periodontal Res</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>38</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>405</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12828658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr96-2041731415618342">
        <label>96</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banes</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>PDGF-BB, IGF-I and mechanical load stimulate DNA synthesis in avian tendon fibroblasts in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Biomech</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>28</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1505</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1513</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8666590</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr97-2041731415618342">
        <label>97</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banes</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinhold</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Gap junctions regulate responses of tendon cells ex vivo to mechanical loading</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>367</volume>(<issue>Suppl.</issue>): <fpage>S356</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>S370</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10546659</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr98-2041731415618342">
        <label>98</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Marymont</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical strain promotes fibroblast gene expression in presence of corticosteroid</article-title>. <source>Connect Tissue Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>65</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17453907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr99-2041731415618342">
        <label>99</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The combined regulation of estrogen and cyclic tension on fibroblast biosynthesis derived from anterior cruciate ligament</article-title>. <source>Matrix Biol</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>323</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>329</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15464364</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr100-2041731415618342">
        <label>100</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudoit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Diversity, topographic differentiation, and positional memory in human fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>99</volume>(<issue>20</issue>): <fpage>12877</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12882</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12297622</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr101-2041731415618342">
        <label>101</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enoch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Peake</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Increased oral fibroblast lifespan is telomerase-independent</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>88</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>916</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>921</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19783799</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr102-2041731415618342">
        <label>102</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enoch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peake</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>&#x201C;Young&#x201D; oral fibroblasts are geno/phenotypically distinct</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>89</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1407</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21098492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr103-2041731415618342">
        <label>103</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Tensile forces attenuate estrogen-stimulated collagen synthesis in the ACL</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>317</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1221</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15094400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr104-2041731415618342">
        <label>104</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taunton</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A survey of injuries to the anterior cruciate ligament of the knee in female basketball players</article-title>. <source>Int J Sports Med</source>
<year>1985</year>; <volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>314</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>316</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4077357</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr105-2041731415618342">
        <label>105</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Knee injuries in female athletes</article-title>. <source>Sports Med</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>288</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>302</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7604201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr106-2041731415618342">
        <label>106</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zelisko</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A comparison of men&#x2019;s and women&#x2019;s professional basketball injuries</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>
<year>1982</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>297</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>299</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6814271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr107-2041731415618342">
        <label>107</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of tension-force on plasminogen activator activity from human periodontal ligament cells</article-title>. <source>J Periodontal Res</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>308</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>314</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9138197</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr108-2041731415618342">
        <label>108</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werb</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mainardi</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vater</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Endogenous activation of latent collagenase by rheumatoid synovial cells</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>1977</year>; <volume>296</volume>(<issue>18</issue>): <fpage>1017</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1023</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">66627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr109-2041731415618342">
        <label>109</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stress enhances expression and production of plasminogen activator in aging human periodontal ligament cells</article-title>. <source>Mech Ageing Dev</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>112</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>217</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>231</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10687926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr110-2041731415618342">
        <label>110</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Archambault</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elfervig-Wall</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Rabbit tendon cells produce MMP-3 in response to fluid flow without significant calcium transients</article-title>. <source>J Biomech</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>303</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>309</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11858805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr111-2041731415618342">
        <label>111</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnoczky</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavagnino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Activation of stress-activated protein kinases (SAPK) in tendon cells following cyclic strain: the effects of strain frequency, strain magnitude, and cytosolic calcium</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>947</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>952</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12382958</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr112-2041731415618342">
        <label>112</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banes</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Horesovsky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical load stimulates expression of novel genes in vivo and in vitro in avian flexor tendon cells</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>141</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>153</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10367022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr113-2041731415618342">
        <label>113</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagakura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsujii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The relationship of VEGF and PGE2 expression to extracellular matrix remodelling of the tenosynovium in the carpal tunnel syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Pathol</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>204</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>605</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>612</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15538733</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr114-2041731415618342">
        <label>114</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Interleukin-1beta increases elasticity of human bioartificial tendons</article-title>. <source>Tissue Eng</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>2913</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2925</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17518659</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr115-2041731415618342">
        <label>115</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexopoulos</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>IL-1beta decreases the elastic modulus of human tenocytes</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>101</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>189</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16627678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr116-2041731415618342">
        <label>116</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ralphs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Waggett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Actin stress fibres and cell-cell adhesion molecules in tendons: organisation in vivo and response to mechanical loading of tendon cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>Matrix Biol</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>67</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11827794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr117-2041731415618342">
        <label>117</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bynum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Almekinders</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>ATP modulates load-inducible IL-1&#x3B2;, COX 2, and MMP-3 gene expression in human tendon cells</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biochem</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>89</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>556</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>562</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12761889</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr118-2041731415618342">
        <label>118</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Otey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Connexin 43 is localized with actin in tenocytes</article-title>. <source>Cell Motil Cytoskeleton</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>121</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>130</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183550</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr119-2041731415618342">
        <label>119</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Piesco</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Low magnitude of tensile strain inhibits IL-1beta-dependent induction of pro-inflammatory cytokines and induces synthesis of IL-10 in human periodontal ligament cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>80</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1416</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1420</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11437211</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr120-2041731415618342">
        <label>120</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Piesco</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Signaling by mechanical strain involves transcriptional regulation of proinflammatory genes in human periodontal ligament cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>Bone</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>547</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>552</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11934644</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr121-2041731415618342">
        <label>121</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pertolani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Interleukin-10: an anti-inflammatory cytokine with therapeutic potential</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Allergy</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1164</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1171</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10469024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr122-2041731415618342">
        <label>122</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohzeki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of cellular aging on the induction of cyclooxygenase-2 by mechanical stress in human periodontal ligament cells</article-title>. <source>Mech Ageing Dev</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>108</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>151</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>163</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10400308</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr123-2041731415618342">
        <label>123</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kikuiri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic tension force activates nitric oxide production in cultured human periodontal ligament cells</article-title>. <source>J Periodontol</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>71</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>533</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>539</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10807114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr124-2041731415618342">
        <label>124</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Archambault</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Stretch and interleukin-1beta induce matrix metalloproteinases in rabbit tendon cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>36</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11853088</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr125-2041731415618342">
        <label>125</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garvin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Novel system for engineering bioartificial tendons and application of mechanical load</article-title>. <source>Tissue Eng</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>967</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>979</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14633381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr126-2041731415618342">
        <label>126</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Triantafillopoulos</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Banes</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>KF</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Nandrolone decanoate and load increase remodeling and strength in human supraspinatus bioartificial tendons</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>934</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>943</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15150040</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr127-2041731415618342">
        <label>127</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Proliferation and differentiation of human osteoblastic cells associated with differential activation of MAP kinases in response to epidermal growth factor, hypoxia, and mechanical stress in vitro</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>249</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>350</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>354</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9712699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr128-2041731415618342">
        <label>128</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanzaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclical tensile force on periodontal ligament cells inhibits osteoclastogenesis through OPG induction</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>85</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>457</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>462</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16632761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr129-2041731415618342">
        <label>129</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ateshian</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A Conewise Linear Elasticity mixture model for the analysis of tension-compression nonlinearity in articular cartilage</article-title>. <source>J Biomech Eng</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>122</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>576</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>586</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11192377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr130-2041731415618342">
        <label>130</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopacz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Experimental verification of the roles of intrinsic matrix viscoelasticity and tension-compression nonlinearity in the biphasic response of cartilage</article-title>. <source>J Biomech Eng</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>125</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>84</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12661200</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr131-2041731415618342">
        <label>131</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>S-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahapatra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Strategies for osteochondral repair: focus on scaffolds</article-title>. <source>J Tissue Eng</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>5</volume>: 2041731414541850.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr132-2041731415618342">
        <label>132</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Role of NF-&#x3BA;B transcription factors in antiinflammatory and proinflammatory actions of mechanical signals</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>50</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>3541</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3548</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15529376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr133-2041731415618342">
        <label>133</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yorimitsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Interleukin-4 downregulates the cyclic tensile stress-induced matrix metalloproteinases-13 and cathepsin B expression by rat normal chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Acta Med Okayama</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>62</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>119</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>126</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18464888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr134-2041731415618342">
        <label>134</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dossumbekova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anghelina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Biomechanical signals inhibit IKK activity to attenuate NF-&#x3BA;B transcription activity in inflamed chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>56</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>3284</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17907174</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr135-2041731415618342">
        <label>135</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic mechanical stress induces extracellular matrix degradation in cultured chondrocytes via gene expression of matrix metalloproteinases and interleukin-1</article-title>. <source>J Biochem</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>125</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>966</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>975</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10220591</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr136-2041731415618342">
        <label>136</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Asada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic tensile stretch on bovine articular chondrocytes inhibits protein kinase C activity</article-title>. <source>J Lab Clin Med</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>130</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>209</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>215</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9280149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr137-2041731415618342">
        <label>137</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gassner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgescu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic tensile stress exerts antiinflammatory actions on chondrocytes by inhibiting inducible nitric oxide synthase</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>163</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>2187</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2192</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10438960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr138-2041731415618342">
        <label>138</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gassner</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Studer</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Interaction of strain and interleukin-1 in articular cartilage: effects on proteoglycan synthesis in chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>389</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>394</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11071247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr139-2041731415618342">
        <label>139</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmvall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Camper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Chondrocyte and chondrosarcoma cell integrins with affinity for collagen type II and their response to mechanical stress</article-title>. <source>Exp Cell Res</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>221</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>496</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>503</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7493650</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr140-2041731415618342">
        <label>140</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasty</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic equibiaxial tensile strain induces both anabolic and catabolic responses in articular chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>404</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17913398</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr141-2041731415618342">
        <label>141</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lahiji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Polotsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hungerford</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic strain stimulates proliferative capacity, &#x3B1;2 and &#x3B1;5 integrin, gene marker expression by human articular chondrocytes propagated on flexible silicone membranes</article-title>. <source>In Vitro Cell Dev Biol Anim</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>5&#x2013;6</issue>): <fpage>138</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15479117</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr142-2041731415618342">
        <label>142</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anghelina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rath-Deschner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Biomechanical signals exert sustained attenuation of proinflammatory gene induction in articular chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1023</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1032</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr143-2041731415618342">
        <label>143</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsukawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Enhancement of nitric oxide and proteoglycan synthesis due to cyclic tensile strain loaded on chondrocytes attached to fibronectin</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Res</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>53</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>239</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>244</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15167970</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr144-2041731415618342">
        <label>144</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Interleukin-4 protects matrix synthesis in chondrocytes under excessive mechanical stress in vitro</article-title>. <source>Mod Rheumatol</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>296</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>300</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24387648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr145-2041731415618342">
        <label>145</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamanishi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Factors related to degradation of articular cartilagein osteoarthritis: a review</article-title>. <source>Seminars in Arthritis and Rheumatism</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>392</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>399</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9662758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr146-2041731415618342">
        <label>146</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsukawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic tensile stretch loaded on bovine chondrocytes causes depolymerization of hyaluronan: involvement of reactive oxygen species</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>48</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>3151</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14613277</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr147-2041731415618342">
        <label>147</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gassner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic tensile strain suppresses catabolic effects of interleukin-1&#x3B2; in fibrochondrocytes from the temporomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>608</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>617</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11263775</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr148-2041731415618342">
        <label>148</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hukuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical stress induces the expression of high molecular mass heat shock protein in human chondrocytic cell line CS-OKB</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>115</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>119</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10772241</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr149-2041731415618342">
        <label>149</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deschner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rath-Deschner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of matrix metalloproteinase expression by dynamic tensile strain in rat fibrochondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>264</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16290189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr150-2041731415618342">
        <label>150</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deschner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rath-Deschner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wypasek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Biomechanical strain regulates TNFR2 but not TNFR1 in TMJ cells</article-title>. <source>J Biomech</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1541</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1549</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17049356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr151-2041731415618342">
        <label>151</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajjar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Franchini</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mandibular appliance modulates condylar growth through integrins</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>87</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>153</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18218842</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr152-2041731415618342">
        <label>152</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The effect of mechanical loading on the metabolism of growth plate chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Ann Biomed Eng</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>793</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>800</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18278554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr153-2041731415618342">
        <label>153</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lahiji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Polotsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hungerford</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic strain stimulates proliferative capacity, alpha-2 integrin by human articular chrondrocytes from osteoarthritic knee joints</article-title>. <source>Univ Pennsylvania Orthop J</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr154-2041731415618342">
        <label>154</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Suga</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Glycosaminoglycan synthesis in the rat articular disk in response to mechanical stress</article-title>. <source>Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>107</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>401</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7709905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr155-2041731415618342">
        <label>155</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The effects of high magnitude cyclic tensile load on cartilage matrix metabolism in cultured chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cell Biol</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>79</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>601</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>609</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11043401</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr156-2041731415618342">
        <label>156</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anghelina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sjostrom</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Biomechanical signals suppress TAK1 activation to inhibit NF-kappaB transcriptional activation in fibrochondrocytes</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>179</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>6246</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr157-2041731415618342">
        <label>157</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The physiologic basis of continuous passive motion for articular cartilage healing and regeneration</article-title>. <source>Hand Clin</source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>211</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8040199</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr158-2041731415618342">
        <label>158</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of continuous passive motion and immobilization on synovitis and cartilage degradation in antigen induced arthritis</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1714</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1721</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8523351</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr159-2041731415618342">
        <label>159</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyauchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamioka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>AlphaVbeta3 integrin ligands enhance volume-sensitive calcium influx in mechanically stretched osteocytes</article-title>. <source>J Bone Miner Metab</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>498</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>504</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17072743</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr160-2041731415618342">
        <label>160</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Boskovic</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fultz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of expression and activity of four PKC isozymes in confluent and mechanically stimulated UMR-108 osteoblastic cells</article-title>. <source>J Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>189</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>216</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>228</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11598907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr161-2041731415618342">
        <label>161</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Asada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic tensile stretch inhibition of nitric oxide release from osteoblast-like cells is both G protein and actin-dependent</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>126</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>131</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11332608</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr162-2041731415618342">
        <label>162</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pertussis toxin-sensitive G proteins as mediators of stretch-induced decrease in nitric-oxide release of osteoblast-like cells</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>593</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>597</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10459768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr163-2041731415618342">
        <label>163</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic tensile stretch stimulates the release of reactive oxygen species from osteoblast-like cells</article-title>. <source>Calcif Tissue Int</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>76</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>433</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15895284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr164-2041731415618342">
        <label>164</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Granet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vico</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexandre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>MAP and src kinases control the induction of AP-1 members in response to changes in mechanical environment in osteoblastic cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Signal</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>679</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>688</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12020768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr165-2041731415618342">
        <label>165</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Beta-catenin levels influence rapid mechanical responses in osteoblasts</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>283</volume>(<issue>43</issue>): <fpage>29196</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>29205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18723514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr166-2041731415618342">
        <label>166</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimston</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Screen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haskell</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Role of connexin43 in osteoblast response to physical load</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>1068</volume>: <fpage>214</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>224</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16831921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr167-2041731415618342">
        <label>167</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziambaras</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecanda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cyclic stretch enhances gap junctional communication between osteoblastic cells</article-title>. <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>218</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>228</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9495514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr168-2041731415618342">
        <label>168</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coon</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Integrins in mechanotransduction</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>613</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>618</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23797029</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr169-2041731415618342">
        <label>169</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sj&#xF6;str&#xF6;m</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Seunarine</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Investigation of the limits of nanoscale filopodial interactions</article-title>. <source>J Tissue Eng</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>5</volume>: 2041731414536177.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr170-2041731415618342">
        <label>170</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damien</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanyon</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanical strain stimulates osteoblast proliferation through the estrogen receptor in males as well as females</article-title>. <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>2169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11092397</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr171-2041731415618342">
        <label>171</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vico</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafage-Proust</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Interactions between estrogen and mechanical strain effects on U2OS human osteosarcoma cells are not influenced by estrogen receptor type</article-title>. <source>Bone</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>35</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1127</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15542038</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr172-2041731415618342">
        <label>172</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kernan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Genetic dissection of mechanosensory transduction: mechanoreception-defective mutations of Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8011334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>