<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mcb</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Molecular and Cellular Biology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0270-7306</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1098-5549</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16809777</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1592724</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2437-05</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.02437-05</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Ectodomain Shedding of Preadipocyte Factor 1 (Pref-1) by Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha Converting Enzyme (TACE) and Inhibition of Adipocyte Differentiation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Yuhui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sul</surname>
            <given-names>Hei Sook</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff0">Department of Nutritional Sciences and Toxicology, University of California, Berkeley, California 94720</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="cor1">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>Corresponding author. Mailing address: Department of Nutritional Sciences and Toxicology, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720. Phone: (510) 642-3978. Fax: (510) 642-0535. E-mail: <email>hsul@nature.berkeley.edu</email>.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>26</volume>
      <issue>14</issue>
      <fpage>5421</fpage>
      <lpage>5435</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2006, American Society for Microbiology</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zmb01406005421.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Preadipocyte factor 1 (Pref-1), an epidermal growth factor repeat containing transmembrane protein found in the preadipocytes, inhibits adipocyte differentiation in vitro and in vivo. Here, we examined the processing of membrane form of Pref-1A to release the 50-kDa soluble form that inhibits adipocyte differentiation. The ectodomain cleavage of Pref-1 is markedly enhanced by phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate in a dose- and time-dependent manner. The basal and stimulated cleavage is inhibited by the broad metalloproteinase inhibitor GM6001, a fact that suggests that cleavage of membrane Pref-1A is dependent on a metalloproteinase. Next, we showed that release of soluble Pref-1A is inhibited by TAPI-0 and by a tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-3, TIMP-3, that can inhibit tumor necrosis factor alpha converting enzyme (TACE), but not by TIMP-1 or TIMP-2. On the other hand, overexpression of TACE increases Pref-1 cleavage to produce the 50-kDa soluble form. Furthermore, this cleavage was not detected in cells with TACE mutation or with TACE small interfering RNA. TACE-mediated shedding of Pref-1 ectodomain inhibits adipocyte differentiation of 3T3-L1 cells and in Pref-1-null mouse embryo fibroblasts transduced with Pref-1A. Identification of TACE as the major protease responsible for conversion of membrane-bound Pref-1 to the biologically active diffusible form provides a new insight into Pref-1 function in adipocyte differentiation.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>