<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25675253</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4326420</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118280</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-28526</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Stress-Induced Neuroprotective Effects of Epiregulin and Amphiregulin</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">EPR and AR in Neuroprotection</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhan</surname>
            <given-names>Libin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>Luping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hosoi</surname>
            <given-names>Toru</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Okuma</surname>
            <given-names>Yasunobu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nomura</surname>
            <given-names>Yasuyuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff006">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Traditional Chinese Medicine, The Second Affiliated Hospital, Dalian Medical University, Dalian, China</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pharmacology, Graduate School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Hokkaido University, Sapporo, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>College (Institute) of Integrative Medicine, Dalian Medical University, Dalian, China</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff004">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pharmacotherapy, Graduate School of Biomedical and Health Sciences, Hiroshima University, Hiroshima, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff005">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Chiba Institute of Sciences, Choshi, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff006">
<label>6</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pharmacology, Kurume University School of Medicine, Kurume, Fukuoka, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Arai</surname>
            <given-names>Ken</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Academic Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Massachusetts General Hospital/Harvard Medical School, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: TH YO YN. Performed the experiments: L. Zhan. Analyzed the data: L. Zhan. Wrote the paper: L. Zhan L. Zheng.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>nomura_yasuyuki@kurume-u.ac.jp</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <elocation-id>e0118280</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2015 Zhan et al</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Zhan et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0118280.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Members of the epidermal growth factor family play important roles in the regulation of cell growth, proliferation, and survival. However, the specific roles of each epidermal growth factor family member with respect to brain injury are not well understood. Gene chip assay screens have revealed drastic increases in the expression of the epidermal growth factor family members amphiregulin and epiregulin following lipopolysaccharide stimulation, which activates an immune response. Both immune activity and endoplasmic reticulum stress are activated during cerebral ischemia. We found that the expression levels of amphiregulin and epiregulin were significantly increased under conditions of cerebral ischemia. Because endoplasmic reticulum stress increased the expression of amphiregulin and epiregulin in glial cells, endoplasmic reticulum stress may be a key mediatory factor of pathophysiological activity. Recombinant epiregulin and amphiregulin proteins effectively inhibited endoplasmic reticulum stress and the subsequent induction of neuronal cell death. Therefore, the upregulation of the epidermal growth factor family members epiregulin and amphiregulin may play a critical role in preventing endoplasmic reticulum stress-induced cell death, thus providing a potential therapy for brain injury.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was supported in part by a Grant-in-Aid from the Ministry of Education, Science and Culture of Japan and was also supported in part by the Japan-China Sasakawa Medical Fellowship. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="6"/>
        <table-count count="2"/>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Members of the epidermal growth factor (EGF) family are known to stimulate the proliferation, differentiation, and survival of numerous cell types. Most recently, the roles of EGF family members in the brain and central nervous system (CNS) have attracted considerable attention. In particular, the roles of these proteins in neuroprotection have been investigated. EGF has been shown to protect against neurotoxicity or cerebral ischemia-induced dopaminergic neuronal death [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0118280.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Heparin-binding EGF-like growth factor (HB-EGF) has been proven to act as an endogenous neuroprotective agent following brain injury [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0118280.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Transforming growth factor alpha (TGF-&#x3B1;) exerts neurotrophic effects and therefore guarantees neuronal survival and inhibits apoptosis [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Recent studies have suggested that betacellulin (BTC) could stimulate the growth of neural stem cells (NSC) and precursor cells in the brain and also increase neurogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0118280.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p>
      <p>Previous studies of the EGF family members amphiregulin (AR) and epiregulin (EPR) have mainly focused on their roles in cell proliferation and tumorigenesis within the mammary gland, ovary, and other organs as well as glioblastoma. Falk and Fris&#xE9;n [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] reported the expression of AR in the choroid plexus of the ventricular system and the hippocampus of the adult brain and noted that AR may participate in the regulation of NSC proliferation and neurogenesis in those areas. AR expression was found to be upregulated following transection of the sciatic nerve, and the addition of AR was found to stimulate axonal outgrowth from the mouse dorsal root ganglia (DRG); moreover, AR acts as an autocrine survival factor for adult sensory neurons [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0118280.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In a similar study, AR mRNA expression was induced in the DRG of TGF-&#x3B1; knockout mice after sciatic nerve injury [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. These results suggest that AR is important for nerve survival and regeneration. Furthermore, subcutaneous EPR administration has been shown to increase the phosphorylation of the brain EGF receptor ErbB1 in mouse neonates, suggesting the potential effect of EPR on brain development [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. A recent study demonstrated that EPR induces human neuroblastoma cell differentiation via the ERK1/2 signaling pathway [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Although the above-described studies imply a potential neuroprotective effect, studies involving a direct approach and functional studies of AR and EPR in the injured brain and nerve cells are limited.</p>
      <p>In this paper, we induced lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-mediated inflammatory reactions, cerebral ischemia, hypoxia, and endoplasmic reticulum stress (ER Stress) in the brain, primary glial cells, and neuron and demonstrated that these challenges and stress conditions directly resulted in brain and nerve cell damage, including apoptosis. We then investigated the expression patterns of EGF family members, particularly EPR and AR, and their roles in neuroprotection.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="sec003">
        <title>Cell culture</title>
        <p>Primary glial cells were prepared from the whole brains of neonatal (24 h) C57BL/6 mice as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The cells were allowed to grow to confluence in Dulbecco&#x2019;s modified Eagle&#x2019;s medium with 10% (v/v) fetal calf serum, 100 U/ml of penicillin G, and 100 &#x3BC;g/ml of streptomycin (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Mouse neuroblastoma Neuro2a cells which were purchased from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) were maintained in modified Eagle&#x2019;s medium supplemented with 10% (v/v) heat-inactivated fetal calf serum. All cultured cells were maintained at 37&#xB0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>/95% air.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec004">
        <title>Gene chip and quantitative assays</title>
        <p>To investigate the potential induction of inflammatory cytokines following LPS challenge, we screened several potential molecules, including 2 typical pro-inflammatory cytokines and 6 EGF family members, using a gene chip probe array. Primary cultured glial cells were exposed to LPS (10 &#x3BC;g/mL) for 4 h, and total RNA was isolated using TRI REAGENTi (Sigma-Aldrich Corporation, St. Louis, MO, USA). Two independent sets of these glial cells were pooled (25 &#x3BC;g of total RNA/sample) and analyzed using the GeneChip Mouse Expression Set 430A (Affymetrix Inc., San Diego, CA, USA). We entrusted the analysis of our array to GeneticLab Co., Ltd. (Sapporo, Japan).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec005">
        <title>LPS-induced inflammatory reaction</title>
        <p>LPS exposure experiments were conducted to evaluate the time- and dose-dependent responses and investigate the expression of EGF family member mRNA. Primary cultured glial cells were treated with 1 &#x3BC;g/ml of LPS for 0, 1, 2, 4, 8, and 24 h or with gradually increasing LPS doses of 0.01, 0.1, 1, and 10 &#x3BC;g/ml for 4 h. We then collected the cultured cells from the different treatment regimes and isolated the total RNA for real-time polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec006">
        <title>Hypoxia induction in mouse primary glial cells</title>
        <p>Sub-confluent primary cultured glial cells were exposed to a mixture of CO<sub>2</sub> (5%) and N<sub>2</sub> in a humidified incubator (ANX-1, HIRASAWA, Tokyo, Japan) at 37&#xB0;C within a sealed, anaerobic, gloved cabinet containing a catalyst to scavenge free oxygen molecules. The oxygen pressures in the chamber and medium were measured using an oxygen analyzer (Teledyne Technologies, Thousand Oaks, CA, USA) and a blood gas analyzer (ABL-2; Radiometer, Copenhagen, Denmark), respectively. Throughout the incubation period, the oxygen levels in the cabinet were measured using a monitor sensitive to oxygen concentrations &lt;10 ppm. The oxygen pressures in the cultured medium at 30 min, 1 h, 6 h, and 48 h fell to 4.3, 3.0, 2.2, and 2.0 &#xB1; 0.2%, respectively, after transfer into the hypoxic chamber. The medium was then changed and the cells were cultured under normal conditions for the indicated time periods.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec007">
        <title>Murine hypoxic/ischemia model</title>
        <p>The mouse hypoxia/ischemia assay was performed as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In brief, 6-week-old C57BL/6 mice purchased from Charles River (Yokohama, Japan) were anesthetized with halothane (2% in 70% N<sub>2</sub>O:30% O<sub>2</sub>) and in each, the right carotid artery was isolated and double ligated with 4&#x2013;0 surgical thread. The incision was then sutured, and the animals were allowed to recover with free access to food and water for 3 h. To induce hypoxia, each animal was placed in a 500-ml glass jar partially submerged in a temperature-controlled water bath and exposed to a humidified gas mixture of 6% O<sub>2</sub>/balance N<sub>2</sub> for 30-min intervals. The animals were then allowed to recover in room air for 30 min before returning to their cages with free access to food and water. Animals that underwent surgical separation but not ligation of the right common carotid artery and were subjected to hypoxia were used as sham-operated controls. All animal experiments were carried out in accordance with the National Institutes of Health Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals and were approved by the animal care and use committee of Hokkaido University.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec008">
        <title>ER stress and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) leakage assay</title>
        <p>Primary glial cells were cultured as described above until unilaminar cells covered 70% of the flask. The cells were then stimulated with 3 &#x3BC;g/ml of tunicamycin (Tm) for 0, 3, 6, 12, 24, and 48 h, after which total RNA was extracted for RT-PCR. To investigate the neuroprotective effects of EPR and AR, Neuro2a cells were pretreated with recombinant EPR (0, 0.01, 0.03, 0.1, and 1 nM) and AR (0, 0.001, 0.01, 0.03, 0.1, and 1 nM) proteins diluted in 10% serum for 1 h. Next, 1 &#x3BC;g/ml of Tm was added to the recombinant protein-treated cells, followed by a 48-h incubation. The viability of Neuro2a cells following Tm stimulation was estimated by the LDH leakage assay and a cytotoxicity detection kit (Roche Molecular Biochemicals, Indianapolis, IN, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. The LDH activity was measured as the optimal density at 492 nm, and LDH leakage (%) was defined as the ratio of LDH activity in the culture medium to the total activity.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec009">
        <title>RT-PCR analysis</title>
        <p>RT-PCR was performed as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Specifically, cDNA was synthesized from total RNA via reverse transcription with 100 U of Superscript III Reverse Transcriptase and Oligo (dt)<sub>12&#x2013;18</sub> (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) in a 20-&#x3BC;l reaction mixture containing Superscript buffer, 1 mM dNTP mix, 10 mM dithiothreitol, and 40 U of RNase inhibitor. For PCR amplification, 1.2 &#x3BC;L of cDNA was added to 12 &#x3BC;L of a reaction mix containing 0.2 &#x3BC;M of each primer, 0.2 &#x3BC;M of dNTP mix, 0.6 U of Taq polymerase, and reaction buffer. PCR was performed in a DNA Thermal Cycler (GeneAmp PCR System 9700; Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). The primers for each PCR are presented in <xref rid="pone.0118280.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec010">
        <title>Western blot analysis</title>
        <p>Cultured Neuro2a cells were collected, washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), and lysed in a lysis buffer. The protein concentrations were measured using the Bio-Rad Protein Assay kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA). The total protein extracts were then fractionated by SDS-PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose membranes at 4&#xB0;C. The membranes were subsequently incubated in blocking buffer at room temperature followed by an overnight incubation with a primary antibody at 4&#xB0;C. The membranes were then incubated with a horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-labeled secondary antibody diluted 1:2000 in Tris-buffered saline + Tween-20 with 5% milk for 1 h at room temperature. HRP-labeled antibodies bound to the membranes were detected by chemiluminescence.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec011">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Statistical analyses were performed using Excel (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA, USA). A 1-way analysis of variance was used to determine the differences between the groups (significance level, P &lt; 0.05; t-test) in the software package SPSS 16.0 (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). The data are presented as mean &#xB1; standard errors of the mean, and each experiment was performed in triplicates.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec012">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec013">
        <title>The EPR and AR expression patterns in response to LPS challenge</title>
        <p>To evaluate the roles of EGF family members during inflammatory reactions, we measured the expression levels of the pro-inflammatory cytokines inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) and cyclooxygenase-2 (Cox-2) in primary cultured glial cells using a Gene Chip Probe Array. The results indicated that the expression of both investigated pro-inflammatory cytokines was induced significantly following LPS stimulation (<xref rid="pone.0118280.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Under these conditions, we found that the expression of both EPR and AR was significantly induced relative to that of other EGF family members (<xref rid="pone.0118280.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), suggesting that EPR and AR may play important roles during inflammatory reactions in the brain and nerve cells.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0118280.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118280.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Fold changes in pro-inflammatory cytokines expression following LPS stimulation.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0118280.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0118280.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pro-inflammatory cytokines</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold change</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">iNOS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cox-2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0118280.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118280.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Fold changes in EGF family member expression following LPS stimulation.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0118280.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0118280.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EGF family members</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold change</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amphiregulin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epiregulin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EGF</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Betacellulin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB-EGF</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGF-a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>A time- and dose-dependent LPS stimulation experiment was then performed in primary glial cells to further investigate the EPR and AR expression levels. Following LPS stimulation, the expression patterns of AR, EPR, EGF, BTC, HB-EGF, and TGF-&#x3B1; were investigated by RT-PCR. All EGF members demonstrated similar expression patterns. Specifically, after LPS stimulation, the expression levels increased gradually before reaching a peak level at 4 h and then decreased to the minimum expression level at 24 h. Significant increases in EPR and AR mRNA levels were observed at 4 h when compared with the control levels (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). We observed a significant increase in AR expression when using either 1 or 10 &#x3BC;g/mL of LPS to stimulate primary glial cells (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>). The expression levels of other EGF family members are presented in <xref rid="pone.0118280.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0118280.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118280.g001</object-id>
          <label>Fig 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Induction of epiregulin (EPR) and amphiregulin (AR) mRNA expression in primary glial cells following lipopolysaccharide (LPS) treatment (time course and dose course).</title>
            <p>(A) Total RNA was isolated from cells exposed to LPS (1 &#x3BC;g/ml) for the indicated time periods and subjected to RT-PCR. (B) Total RNA was isolated from cells exposed to LPS (4 h) at the indicated concentrations and subjected to RT-PCR. Data are presented as the means &#xB1; standard errors from 3 separate experiments. *p &lt; 0.05 compared with the control.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0118280.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec014">
        <title>Upregulation of EPR and AR following ischemia and hypoxia</title>
        <p>We cultured primary glial cells under hypoxic conditions <italic>in vitro</italic> and used RT-PCR to reveal that the levels of all EGF family members after 3 h in culture increased above the control levels before gradually decreasing. We also identified significant increases in AR expression after 3 h and 6 h in culture. In addition, the HB-EGF levels were also elevated, with a peak value appearing at 3 h (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0118280.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>.). We further investigated the expression patterns of AR, EPR, EGF, BTC, HB-EGF, and TGF-&#x3B1; in the cortex, striatum, and hippocampus via RT-PCR following an <italic>in vivo</italic> ischemia assay. In the cortex, we observed significant differences in the levels of EPR mRNA at 24 h when compared with the control levels. This increase was found to persist until 48 h. The high expression levels of EPR and BTC were maintained throughout the analysis period, and significant differences in the control levels were observed between 6 h and 48 h (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). We did not observe any significant differences in the expression levels of other EGF family members when compared with the control levels (<xref rid="pone.0118280.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3A Fig</xref>.). Similar EGF family member expression patterns were observed in the striatum (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0118280.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3B Fig</xref>.). In the hippocampus, only AR expression increased significantly, and this increase persisted until 48 h after ischemia (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0118280.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3C Fig</xref>.).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0118280.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118280.g002</object-id>
          <label>Fig 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Induction of epiregulin (EPR) and amphiregulin (AR) mRNA expression in primary glial cells under hypoxic conditions.</title>
            <p>Total RNA was isolated from cells exposed to hypoxic conditions for the indicated time periods and subjected to RT-PCR. Data are presented as the means &#xB1; standard errors from 3 separate experiments. *p &lt; 0.05 compared with the control.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0118280.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0118280.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118280.g003</object-id>
          <label>Fig 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Time course analysis of epiregulin (EPR) and amphiregulin (AR) mRNA expression in the ischemic cerebral cortex.</title>
            <p>(A) The injured cortex, (B) striatum, and (C) hippocampus were obtained at various time points (control, 6, 12, 24, and 48 h) following a 30-min hypoxia/ischemia exposure; total RNA was extracted and subjected to RT-PCR. Data are presented as means &#xB1; standard errors. Control samples were obtained at 3 h after the sham operation (cont). *p &lt; 0.05 compared with the sham-operated mice.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0118280.g003"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec015">
        <title>EPR and AR play important roles in ER Stress in glial and Neuro2a cells</title>
        <p>We next observed the expression patterns of AR, EPR, EGF, BTC, HB-EGF, and TGF-&#x3B1; in primary glial cells for 0, 3, 6, 12, and 24 h after the administration of the ER stress antileptic Tm, which induces the unfolded protein production by inhibiting N-linked glycosylation. We found that the expression levels of all EGF family members were increased after 3 h and that there were significant increases in the levels of AR and EPR during the first 6 h; these levels subsequently decreased over time (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). However, the expression levels of other family members were maintained at slightly higher levels than those observed in the control cells (<xref rid="pone.0118280.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Fig</xref>.). LDH leakage assays were performed to evaluate the protective effects of recombinant AR and EPR following Tm stimulation, which was used to induce ER Stress in Neuro2a cells. When compared with the control group, we did not observe any statistically significant differences in the LDH leakage gradient concentrations in the recombinant pretreated group, suggesting that the recombinant protein did not induce any toxicity in the Neuro2a cells. However, LDH leakage increased drastically after the addition of Tm. We also found that LDH leakage in the Tm/recombinant pretreated group decreased significantly with increasing concentrations of recombinant AR and EPR recombinant (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A and B</xref>). Western blotting was then performed to investigate the expression of Transcriptional factor CCAAT/enhancer-binding protein-homologous protein (CHOP) and glucose-regulated protein 78 (GRP78) following Tm stimulation in cells pretreated with recombinant AR and EPR. We found no impact on the expression of CHOP and GRP78 in cells treated with AR and EPR alone. The addition of Tm significantly upregulated the expression of both CHOP and GRP78, and this elevated expression gradually reversed in accordance with increasing concentrations of recombinant AR and EPR (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A and B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0118280.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118280.g004</object-id>
          <label>Fig 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Induction of epiregulin (EPR) and amphiregulin (AR) mRNA expression in primary glial cells following Tm treatment.</title>
            <p>Total RNA was isolated from cells exposed to Tm (3 &#x3BC;g/ml) for the indicated periods and subjected to RT-PCR. Data are presented as the means &#xB1; standard errors from 3 separate experiments. *p &lt; 0.05 compared with the control.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0118280.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0118280.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118280.g005</object-id>
          <label>Fig 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Epiregulin (EPR) and amphiregulin (AR) inhibited cell death in Neuro2a cells.</title>
            <p>The cells were pretreated with EPR (0.01, 0.03, 0.1, and 1 nM) and AR (0.001, 0.01, 0.03, 0.1, and 1 nM) for 1 h and subsequently treated according to the indicated conditions. (A) EPR reduced the release of lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) at 48 h after Tm (1 &#x3BC;g/mL) treatment. (B) AR reduced the release of LDH at 48 h after Tm (1 &#x3BC;g/mL) treatment. The LDH released into the medium was expressed as a percentage of the control value. The data represent the average of 4 independent experiments for each sample. *p &lt; 0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0118280.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0118280.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118280.g006</object-id>
          <label>Fig 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Epiregulin (EPR) and amphiregulin (AR) inhibited endoplasmic reticulum stress in Neuro2a cells.</title>
            <p>Neuro2a cells were pre-incubated with (A) EPR or (B) AR for 1 h and then treated with tunicamycin (Tm) for 24 h. GRP78 and CHOP expression was detected via western blotting. Protein quantification is expressed as the mean &#xB1; standard error of 3 independent experiments. *p &lt; 0.05 compared with the Tm-treated group.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0118280.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Inflammatory reactions, which involve immune responses, are common pathological processes observed in medical clinics. Following LPS stimulation, the levels of 2 pro-inflammatory cytokines were increased in primary glial cells. These increases are considered to be the trigger that initiates an inflammatory reaction. In our study, we screened for EPR and AR expression using a gene chip assay and revealed that the levels of those molecules were drastically higher than those of other EGF family members. A subsequent RT-PCR analysis validated the findings of significant EPR and AR upregulation (<xref rid="pone.0118280.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A and B</xref>). These findings were similar to those observed in a human intestinal epithelial cell line [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Shirasawa <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] also revealed that EPR may play a critical role in both LPS- and peptidoglycan-induced pro-inflammatory cytokine production in macrophages, whereas Nishimura <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] reported that EPR may play an important role in mucosal repair during inflammatory bowel disease. AR has also been reported to induce pro-inflammatory cytokine overexpression in numerous tissues [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Moreover, the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) pathway has been reported to interact with inflammatory and immune responses [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The EGFR/PI3K/Akt and MAPK pathway is considered to induce pro-inflammatory molecule upregulation and cell proliferation [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Based on these studies, it is has been hypothesized that in the brain, AR and EPR are essential for the normal production of pro-inflammatory cytokines involved in the immune response, suggesting that AR and EPR may directly promote inflammatory reactions by inducing pro-inflammatory cytokine production or indirectly stimulate neurogenesis and proliferation by maintaining sufficient numbers of glial cells to attenuate LPS-induced damage.</p>
      <p>ER stress, which is induced by the accumulation of unfolded proteins and the disruption of calcium production in the ER, triggers many rescue responses, including the unfolded-protein response (UPR). Excessive or long-term exposure to ER stress may also induce cell apoptosis [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In addition, ER stress has been implicated in the pathogenesis of numerous diseases, including neurodegenerative diseases resulting from injury or the apoptosis of neurons and glial cells. GRP78 is an important molecular chaperone located in the ER that acts as a central regulator of multiple ER functions such as participation in the UPR and specific anti-apoptotic actions. CHOP is a known apoptosis-enhancing factor that is present during ER stress. The levels of GRP78 and CHOP expression increase during severe ER stress. In contrast, when ER stress is efficiently inhibited, the levels of GRP78 and CHOP should decrease [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Given these findings, GRP78 and CHOP could serve as potential molecular markers of ER stress. We found the increased expression of EPR and AR mRNA following Tm stimulation particularly interesting. Therefore, in our study we used Tm to induce ER stress in primary glial cells and added recombinant EPR and AR in an attempt to inhibit the ER stress response. We found that the expression levels of GRP78 and CHOP protein decreased as the concentrations of added recombinant EPR and AR increased. The downregulation of GRP78 suggests that molecular chaperone recruitment decreased, which correlated with the inhibited production and accumulation of unfolded proteins. Tm induced ER stress and the upregulation of GRP78 functioned as molecular chaperone in cells. The subsequent expression of AR and EPR could attenuate ER stress and UPR, and then suppressing the upregulation of GRP78. Based on the present references, we deduced that the mechanisms underlying the downregulation of GRP78 after expression of AR and EPR involved in EGFR and PI3K/AKT pathway. Intense and persistent ER stress could result in cell apoptosis. It has been reported AR and EPR could inhibit cell apoptosis via the activation of EGFR and PI3K/AKT pathway. Therefore, we made a hypothesis that AR and EPR may inhibit cell apoptosis and attenuate ER stress and UPR by activating AR and EPR and then decrease the expression of GRP78 [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0118280.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The PERK-eIF2&#x3B1;-ATF4 pathway is known to be required for adequate CHOP expression. When severe ER stress occurs, PERK may induce CHOP to promote cell apoptosis by mediating the arrest of cell cycle and protein production [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0118280.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The downregulation of CHOP indicates that the partial restoration of the metabolic pathway in stressed cells suggests the attenuation of apoptosis. Taken together, these findings suggest that EPR and AR function as neuroprotective factors by reducing the need for CHOP and GRP78. The inhibition of CHOP and GRP78, which could be considered the result of a successful UPR, in turn leads to the attenuation of ER stress and subsequent inhibition of apoptosis.</p>
      <p>Following hypoxia or cerebral ischemia, affected brain cells undergo a complex series of events that lead to cell death [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Cerebral ischemia is a pathophysiological ER stressor and hypoxia is known for inducing ER stress in primary glial cells [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Several studies have shown that ischemic injury severely impairs ER function, which in turn triggers the termination of protein translation and apoptosis [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0118280.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. These findings suggest that the ER plays an important role in cerebral ischemia. Therefore, reducing ER stress and inducing the UPR survival pathway may comprise a therapeutic method for blocking the pathological process induced by cerebral ischemia [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Our data revealed that the upregulation of EGF family members over a short period of time is most likely an important response to the ER stress induced by hypoxic/ischemia in either the tissues or cells. In particular, the expression levels of EPR and particularly AR were remarkably upregulated relative to the control levels in response to hypoxic/ischemic conditions in the cortex and striatum, a finding that is consistent with the results arising from the ER stress-inducing Tm assay presented in <xref rid="pone.0118280.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>. This direct proof associates EPR, AR, and ischemia/hypoxia with ER stress. Moreover, in the hippocampus, which is involved in study and memory, only AR expression exhibited a significant and persistent increase, implying a novel role for AR in protecting the hippocampal neurons. Therefore, it appears likely that EPR and AR are involved in the prevention of cellular death consequent to cerebral ischemia or hypoxia by inhibiting ER stress.</p>
      <p>ER stress is not only associated with ischemia and hypoxia but also plays an important role in inflammatory reactions. LPS has been reported as a stressor in primary glial cells and induce ER stress [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Recent studies have indicated that inflammatory reactions may induce ER stress. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying these processes remain unclear. ER stress-inducing inflammatory factors have been reported to be mediated by reactive oxygen species (ROS). Therefore, inflammatory reactions may produce ROS that lead to calcium exhaustion and the accumulation of unfolded proteins in the ER, both of which may induce ER stress [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In addition, the activation of the UPR signaling pathway during ER stress may also suppress inflammatory reactions by blocking NF-&#x3BA;B activation [<xref rid="pone.0118280.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Therefore, the upregulation of EPR and AR could partly contribute to the inhibition of ER stress and subsequently the UPR, which triggers inflammatory reactions, thereby protecting tissues and cells from serious damage.</p>
      <p>Taken together, the results described in this study suggest that ER stress is a critical component of inflammatory reactions and ischemia/hypoxic progression. EPR and AR most likely exert their neuroprotective effects by inhibiting ER stress, and thus provide a potential therapeutic strategy for attenuating the damage exerted by adverse stimuli in the brain or nervous system.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec017">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0118280.s001">
        <label>S1 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Induction of BTC, EGF, HB-EGF, and TGF-&#x3B1; mRNA expression in primary glial cells following LPS treatment (time course and dose course).</title>
          <p>(A) Total RNA was isolated from cells exposed to LPS (1 &#x3BC;g/ml) for the indicated time periods and subjected to RT-PCR. (B) Total RNA was isolated from cells exposed to LPS (4 h) at the indicated concentrations and subjected to RT-PCR. Data are presented as the means &#xB1; standard errors from 3 separate experiments. *p &lt; 0.05 compared with the control.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0118280.s001.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0118280.s002">
        <label>S2 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Induction of BTC, EGF, HB-EGF, and TGF-&#x3B1; mRNA expression in primary glial cells under hypoxic conditions.</title>
          <p>Total RNA was isolated from cells exposed to hypoxic conditions for the indicated time periods and subjected to RT-PCR. Data are presented as the means &#xB1; standard errors from 3 separate experiments. *p &lt; 0.05 compared with the control.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0118280.s002.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0118280.s003">
        <label>S3 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Time course analysis of BTC, EGF, HB-EGF, and TGF-&#x3B1; mRNA expression in the ischemic cerebral cortex.</title>
          <p>(A) The injured cortex, (B) striatum, and (C) hippocampus were obtained at various time points (control, 6, 12, 24, and 48 h) following a 30-min hypoxia/ischemia exposure; total RNA was extracted and subjected to RT-PCR. Data are presented as means &#xB1; standard errors. Control samples were obtained at 3 h after the sham operation (cont). *p &lt; 0.05 compared with sham-operated mice.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0118280.s003.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0118280.s004">
        <label>S4 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Induction of BTC, EGF, HB-EGF, and TGF-&#x3B1; mRNA expression in primary glial cells following Tm treatment.</title>
          <p>Total RNA was isolated from cells exposed to Tm (3 &#x3BC;g/ml) for the indicated periods and subjected to RT-PCR. Data are presented as the means &#xB1; standard errors from 3 separate experiments. *p &lt; 0.05 compared with the control.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0118280.s004.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0118280.s005">
        <label>S1 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Primer sequences used for RT-PCR.</title>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0118280.s005.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Teramoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plumier</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moskowitz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>EGF amplifies the replacement of parvalbumin-expressing striatal interneurons after ischemia</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<volume>111</volume>: <fpage>1125</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1132</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12697732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Moskowitz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Neurogenesis and apoptotic cell death</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>326</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12574524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Epidermal growth factor protects neuronal cells in vivo and in vitro against transient forebrain ischemia- and free radical-induced injuries</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>360</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9538899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mishima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higashiyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The gene for heparin-binding epidermal growth factor-like growth factor is stress-inducible: its role in cerebral ischemia</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>320</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10078883</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chalazonitis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Twardzik</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Transforming growth factor alpha, but not epidermal growth factor, promotes the survival of sensory neurons in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>594</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1740693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>G&#xF3;mez-Gaviro</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sesay</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matheu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Betacellulin promotes cell proliferation in the neural stem cell niche and stimulates neurogenesis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1317</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1322</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1016199109</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22232668</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells stimulate proliferation and neuronal differentiation of retinal progenitor cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e76157</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076157</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24098776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fris&#xE9;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Amphiregulin is a mitogen for adult neural stem cells</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Res</source>
<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>757</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>762</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12205669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dahlin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lundborg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanje</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Early changes in gene expression in the dorsal root ganglia after transection of the sciatic nerve; effects of amphiregulin and PAI-1 on regeneration</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Mol Brain Res</source>
<volume>136</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>74</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15893588</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanje</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Amphiregulin acts as an autocrine survival factor for adult sensory neurons</article-title>. <source>Neuroreport</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>218</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15706222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Xian</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Lack of effects of transforming growth factor-alpha gene knockout on peripheral nerve regeneration may result from compensatory mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Exp Neurol</source>
<volume>172</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>188</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11681850</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Komurasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Common behavioral influences of the ErbB1 ligands transforming growth factor alpha and epiregulin administered to mouse neonates</article-title>. <source>Brain Dev</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>543</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.braindev.2008.01.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18313247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rizzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pittarella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sabbatini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren&#xF2;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Epiregulin induces human SK-N-BE cell differentiation through ERK1/2 signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Growth Factors</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/08977194.2013.795958</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23734838</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hosoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Expression of leptin receptors and induction of IL-1beta transcript in glial cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<volume>273</volume>: <fpage>312</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>315</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10873603</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hosoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Edaravone protects against hypoxia/ischemia- induced endoplasmic reticulum dysfunction</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source>
<volume>311</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>393</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15178695</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hosoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawagishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Brain stem is a direct target for leptin&#x2019;s action in the central nervous system</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<volume>143</volume>: <fpage>3498</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3504</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12193563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sotolongo</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Toll-like receptor 4 differentially regulates epidermal growth factor-related growth factors in response to intestinal mucosal injury</article-title>. <source>Lab Invest</source>
<volume>90</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1295</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1305</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/labinvest.2010.100</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20498653</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inokuchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sekine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Dermatitis due to epiregulin deficiency and a critica role of epiregulin in immune-related responses of keratinocyte and macrophage</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>101</volume>: <fpage>13921</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13926</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15365177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andoh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inatomi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shioya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Amphiregulin and epiregulin expression in neoplastic and inflammatory lesions in the colon</article-title>. <source>Oncol Rep</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>110</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18097582</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sisto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lisi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lofrumento</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ingravallo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitolo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Expression of pro-inflammatory TACE-TNF-&#x3B1;-amphiregulin axis in Sj&#xF6;gren&#x2019;s syndrome salivary glands</article-title>. <source>Histochem Cell Biol</source>
<volume>134</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>353</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00418-010-0735-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20811902</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pastore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mascia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girolomoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The epidermal growth factor receptor system in skin repair and inflammation</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>
<volume>128</volume>: <fpage>1365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1374</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18049451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>c-Src-dependent EGF receptor transactivation contributes to ET-1-induced COX-2 expression in brain microvascular endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>J Neuroinflammation</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>152</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-2094-9-152</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22747786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ferreiro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Resende</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>An endoplasmic-reticulum-specific apoptotic pathway is involved in prion and amyloid-beta peptides neurotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol Dis</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>669</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>678</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16844381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yasumura</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>IRE1 signaling affects cell fate during the unfolded protein response</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>318</volume>: <fpage>944</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>949</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17991856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Berasain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garc&#xED;a-Trevijano</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erroba</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santamar&#xED;a</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Novel role for amphiregulin in protection from liver injury</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>280</volume> (<issue>19</issue>): <fpage>19012</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Puttabyatappa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brogan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vandevoort</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaffin</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>EGF-Like Ligands Mediate Progesterone&#x2019;s Anti-Apoptotic Action on Macaque Granulosa Cells</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>
<volume>88</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>18</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1095/biolreprod.112.103002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23136296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fels</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koumenis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The PERK/eIF2alpha/ATF4 module of the UPR in hypoxia resistance and tumor growth</article-title>. <source>Cancer Biol Ther</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>723</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>728</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16861899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Szegezdi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Logue</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Mediators of endoplasmic reticulum stress-induced apoptosis</article-title>. <source>EMBO Rep</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>880</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>885</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16953201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dirnagl</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iadecola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moskowitz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Pathobiology of ischaemic stroke: an integrated view</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>397</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10441299</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeGracia</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Dysfunction of the unfolded protein response during global brain ischemia and reperfusion</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>462</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>471</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12679723</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref031">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tajiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oyadomari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morioka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ischemia-induced neuronal cell death is mediated by the endoplasmic reticulum stress pathway involving CHOP</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>415</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14752508</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref032">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kintner</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Endoplasmic reticulum Ca2<sup>+</sup> dysregulation and endoplasmic reticulum stress following in vitro neuronal ischemia: role of Na+-K+-Cl- cotransporter</article-title>. <source>J Neurochem</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>1563</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1576</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2008.05501.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18507737</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref033">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mecha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Torrao</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mestre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrillo-Salinas</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mechoulam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cannabidiol protects oligodendrocyte progenitor cells from inflammation-induced apoptosis by attenuating endoplasmic reticulum stress</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Dis</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e331</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddis.2012.71</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22739983</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref034">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Biphasic, bidirectional regulation of NF-kappaB by endoplasmic reticulum stress</article-title>. <source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>2353</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2364</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ARS.2008.2391</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19187000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0118280.ref035">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa quorum-sensing molecule N-(3-oxododecanoyl) homoserine lactone attenuates lipopolysaccharide- induced inflammation by activating the unfolded protein response</article-title>. <source>Biomed Rep</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>238</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24649102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>