<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
  <!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
  <?properties manuscript?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">8205768</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4590</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biochem</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Journal of cellular biochemistry</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0730-2312</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1097-4644</issn>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21381079</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3111753</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.23094</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS277824</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>EGFR signaling suppresses osteoblast differentiation and inhibits expression of master osteoblastic transcription factors Runx2 and Osterix</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>Ji</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shimizu</surname>
            <given-names>Emi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Xianrong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Partridge</surname>
            <given-names>Nicola C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Qin</surname>
            <given-names>Ling</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Basic Science &amp; Craniofacial Biology, New York University College of Dentistry, New York, New York, USA</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Endodontics, New York University College of Dentistry, New York, New York</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Ling Qin, Ph.D. 424D Stemmler Hall, 36<sup>th</sup> Street and Hamilton Walk, Philadelphia, PA 19104. Tel: 215-8986697; Fax: 215-5732133; <email>qinling@mail.med.upenn.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>112</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>1749</fpage>
      <lpage>1760</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p id="P1">The epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) and its ligands regulate key processes of cell biology, such as proliferation, survival, differentiation, migration, and tumorigenesis. We previously showed that EGFR signaling pathway is an important bone regulator and it primarily plays an anabolic role in bone metabolism. In this study, we demonstrated that EGF-like ligands strongly inhibited osteoblast differentiation and mineralization in several lines of osteoblastic cells. Real-time RT-PCR and promoter reporter assays revealed that EGF-like ligands suppressed the expression of both early and late bone marker genes at the transcriptional level in the differentiating osteoblasts via an EGFR-dependent manner. This inhibitory effect of EGFR signaling was not dependent on its mitogenic activity. Furthermore, we demonstrated that EGFR signaling reduced the expression of two major osteoblastic transcription factors Runx2 (type II) and Osterix in osteoblast differentiating cells. EGFR-induced decrease in Runx2 transcriptional activity was confirmed by Runx2 reporter and chromatin immunoprecipitation assays. EGFR signaling increased the protein amounts of transcription corepressors HDAC4 and 6 and overexpression of HDAC4 decreased Runx2 amount in differentiating osteoblasts, implying that HDACs contribute to the down-regulation of Runx2 by EGFR. Moreover, activation of EGFR in undifferentiated osteoprogenitors attenuated the expression of early bone markers and Osterix and decreased Runx2 protein amounts. Together with our previous data that EGFR stimulates osteoprogenitor proliferation and that blocking EGFR activity in osteoblast lineage cells results in fewer osteoprogenitors and osteopenic phenotype, we conclude that EGFR signaling is important for maintaining osteoprogenitor population at an undifferentiated stage.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>EGFR</kwd>
        <kwd>osteoblast differentiation</kwd>
        <kwd>Runx2</kwd>
        <kwd>osterix</kwd>
        <kwd>HDAC</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <contract-num rid="DK1">K01 DK071988-05
				||DK</contract-num>
      <contract-sponsor id="DK1">National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases  : NIDDK</contract-sponsor>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>